<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Posts on Errata</title><link>https://sjchiass.github.io/website/posts/</link><description>Recent content in Posts on Errata</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 09 May 2021 08:47:04 -0400</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://sjchiass.github.io/website/posts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Hugo with GH actions</title><link>https://sjchiass.github.io/website/posts/misc/2021_w19_linux/</link><pubDate>Sun, 09 May 2021 08:47:04 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://sjchiass.github.io/website/posts/misc/2021_w19_linux/</guid><description>My newbie GH Action setup for updating my website</description><content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2 id="basic-idea">Basic idea</h2>
<p>I have GitHub actions build the Hugo website then I use scp to copy it over to my remote server.</p>
<h2 id="ssh-keys">SSH keys</h2>
<p>The idea here is to generate an SSH key on your computer. You then send the public key to the remote server, and you paste your private key into GitHub. That way GitHub can log into your server and dump the new files there.</p>
<p>If ever something goes wrong with GitHub secrets, you can log into your server and delete the key.</p>
<p>First, generate an ssh key on your computer. Put it in a separate place so that you don&rsquo;t mix it up with other keys.</p>
<div class="highlight"><pre style="color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4"><code class="language-bash" data-lang="bash">ssh-keygen -f ~/temp/id_rsa
</code></pre></div><p>You can then send the public key to your server. If you want to get rid of the key, delete it from <code>authorized_keys</code>.</p>
<div class="highlight"><pre style="color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4"><code class="language-bash" data-lang="bash">cat ~/temp/id_rsa.pub | ssh user@hostname <span style="color:#e6db74">&#39;cat &gt;&gt; .ssh/authorized_keys&#39;</span>
</code></pre></div><p>Pasting a secret into GitHub is pretty easy. In your repository, navigate here:</p>
<pre><code>Settings -&gt; Secrets -&gt; New repository secret
</code></pre><p>Name the secret <code>KEY</code> and paste in the private key contents. You can read more about GitHub secrets here: <a href="https://docs.github.com/en/actions/reference/encrypted-secrets">https://docs.github.com/en/actions/reference/encrypted-secrets</a></p>
<p>If you added a passphrase to your key, add it to a <code>PASSPHRASE</code> secret.</p>
<h2 id="github-action">GitHub action</h2>
<p>Here is my full <code>.yml</code> file. The last step <code>Upload</code> is when the files are copied.</p>
<p>You can read more about <code>scp-action</code> here: <a href="https://github.com/appleboy/scp-action">https://github.com/appleboy/scp-action</a></p>
<p>I stuck to the basic Hugo action. I tried with the latest version of Hugo, but that didn&rsquo;t work. You can tweak your actions by reading the README: <a href="https://github.com/peaceiris/actions-hugo">https://github.com/peaceiris/actions-hugo</a></p>
<pre><code>name: hugo deploy

on:
  push:
    branches:
      - master

jobs:
  deploy:
    runs-on: ubuntu-latest
    steps:
      - uses: actions/checkout@v2
        with:
          submodules: true  # Fetch Hugo themes (true OR recursive)
          fetch-depth: 0    # Fetch all history for .GitInfo and .Lastmod

      - name: Setup Hugo
        uses: peaceiris/actions-hugo@v2
        with:
          hugo-version: '0.81.0'
          extended: true

      - name: Build
        run: hugo --minify

      - name: Upload
        uses: appleboy/scp-action@master
        with:
          username: ${{ secrets.USERNAME }}
          host: ${{ secrets.HOST }}
          port: ${{ secrets.PORT }}
          passphrase: ${{ secrets.PASSPHRASE }}
          key: ${{ secrets.KEY }}
          source: &quot;./public&quot;
          target: &quot;gh_page&quot;
          rm: true
</code></pre><p>I also want to deploy to GitHub pages, so I add these steps at the end.</p>
<p>The <code>sed</code> command edits my Hugo <code>config.toml</code> to point to the GH pages address. I can then deploy, and the site will work properly. If you don&rsquo;t do this, the site will be broken.</p>
<pre><code>      - name: Config
        run: |
          sed -i &quot;s=${{ secrets.DO_DOMAIN }}=${{ secrets.GH_DOMAIN }}=&quot; config.toml
          hugo --minify

      - name: Deploy
        uses: peaceiris/actions-gh-pages@v3
        with:
          github_token: ${{ secrets.GITHUB_TOKEN }}
          publish_dir: ./public
</code></pre><h2 id="secrets">Secrets</h2>
<p>Add these other secrets to GitHub. You have to specify the <code>USERNAME</code>, <code>HOST</code> AND <code>PORT</code> separately.</p>
<ul>
<li><code>USERNAME</code> the user you want to log into for the scp</li>
<li><code>HOST</code> probably an IP address</li>
<li><code>PORT</code> the port number, probably 22 if kept the default</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="final-step-cron-job">Final step: cron job</h2>
<p>On your server, run <code>sudo crontab -e</code> to start a regular job as <code>ROOT</code>. This will regularly copy your files to the web server.</p>
<p>A file will open in your console, where you can paste</p>
<pre><code>0 * * * * rsync -avh /home/username/gh_page/public/ /var/www/example.com/
</code></pre>]]></content></item><item><title>BBQ baked beans in an Instant Pot</title><link>https://sjchiass.github.io/website/posts/food/2021_w16_food/</link><pubDate>Tue, 20 Apr 2021 07:21:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sjchiass.github.io/website/posts/food/2021_w16_food/</guid><description>I used BBQ sauce to season beans and then cooked them for a few hours. With the BBQ sauce they take a longer time to cook. The results are very tasty.</description><content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2 id="background">Background</h2>
<p>I bought an Instant Pot months ago, and I&rsquo;ve been cooking a lot of beans in it. Most of the time I make chili-like beans and soups, but one day I decided to try BBQ sauce as the only seasoning.</p>
<p>The internet warns about cooking beans in any kind of acid. They&rsquo;ll be hard they say. The acidic BBQ sauce I use does make the beans more stubborn to cook.</p>
<p>This is my second time using this recipe. The beans are easy to make, well-cooked and tasty.</p>
<h2 id="video">Video</h2>

<div style="position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;">
  <iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/_RcG3bzT_z4" style="position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;" allowfullscreen title="YouTube Video"></iframe>
</div>

<h2 id="results">Results</h2>
<p>Very tender beans.</p>
<p><img src="IMG_1168.JPG" alt="Beans in a laddle"></p>
<h2 id="ingredients">Ingredients</h2>
<p>These quantities are enough to nearly enough to fill a 6Qt Instant Pot to its half-fill mark, which is the maximum they recommend for beans.</p>
<ul>
<li>2 cups of white beans (I use great Northern beans)</li>
<li>6 cups of water</li>
<li>3/4 cups of BBQ sauce</li>
<li>4 frozen sausages</li>
</ul>
<p>At the store, look for a BBQ sauce with ingredients like: sugar, vinegar, molasses, and tomato paste. They may come in a different order. The sauce ends up not tasting like BBQ sauce at all after cooking. It really just tastes mildly like sweet tangy molasses. The tomato paste mostly contributes to the colour.</p>
<h2 id="recipe">Recipe</h2>
<p>The acidity of the BBQ sauce makes the beans cook more slowly, so they have to be stirred and simmered half way. Normally beans only require 30-40 minutes of high pressure with natural release.</p>
<p>There&rsquo;s some debate over whether you should soak beans before cooking them in an Instant Pot. It depends on the beans and the recipe. Within the same bag of beans, some beans cook more slowly. A bit of soaking helps.</p>
<ul>
<li>Soak beans in cool water for 15 minutes, discard water</li>
<li>Place 2 cups beans, 6 cups water, 3/4 cups BBQ sauce, and sausages in the Instant Pot</li>
<li>Stir</li>
<li>Pressure cook on high for 40 minutes, with natural release (30 minutes)
<ul>
<li>Note: it may take 20 minutes or more for the pressure to build</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Open, stir, and simmer on low for 20 minutes</li>
<li>Again pressure cook for 15 minutes, this time quick releasing to save time (5 minutes)</li>
<li>Simmer on low again for 10 minutes</li>
</ul>
<p>After the second simmer the sauce will have thickened and the beans will be very tender. The sausages will be fork-tender and will be falling apart.</p>
<h2 id="further-thoughts">Further thoughts</h2>
<p>I think the act of opening the lid, stirring the beans, and simmering them a little is what helps the beans soften. I think they just need to be moved around a little.</p>
<p>Pressure cooking doesn&rsquo;t seem to jostle the beans at all. While they pressure cook and they natural release, the high pressure prevents any boiling. The air is saturated with steam so the hot water can&rsquo;t create any more (ie: boil).</p>
<p>It may work to do</p>
<ul>
<li>20-30 minutes for the ingredients to heat up and the pressure to build</li>
<li>10 minutes high pressure cook, natural release (30 minutes)</li>
<li>10 minutes stir and simmer on low</li>
<li>10 minutes high pressure cook, natural release (30 minutes)</li>
<li>10 minutes stir and simmer on low</li>
</ul>
<p>I&rsquo;ll try it next time with this recipe. Other bean recipes work fine with a single pressure cook.</p>
]]></content></item><item><title>Strange photos of playing cats</title><link>https://sjchiass.github.io/website/posts/cats/2021_w16_cats/</link><pubDate>Sun, 18 Apr 2021 15:49:26 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://sjchiass.github.io/website/posts/cats/2021_w16_cats/</guid><description>I went through old cat photos and found sound funny ones.</description><content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>(Looks like Hugo supports emojis: <a href="https://gohugo.io/functions/emojify/">https://gohugo.io/functions/emojify/</a> I use them below.)</p>
<h3 id="eating-cat-grass">Eating cat grass</h3>
<figure>
    <img src="IMG_0245.JPG"
         alt="Getting ready to bite the grass"/> <figcaption>
            <p>Getting ready to bite the grass</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>The cat is bad at getting the grass in its mouth, so it opens it as big as possible and lunges at it.</p>
<figure>
    <img src="IMG_0246.JPG"
         alt="Munch munch tasty grass"/> <figcaption>
            <p>Munch munch tasty grass</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>When they have grass in their mouths they masticate very noisily. 🤤</p>
<h3 id="playing-with-the-yellow-floof">Playing with the yellow floof</h3>
<figure>
    <img src="IMG_0284.JPG"
         alt="Standing cat with oddly concentrated face"/> <figcaption>
            <p>Standing cat with oddly concentrated face</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>This cat has a habit of scrunching its face together sometimes.</p>
<figure>
    <img src="IMG_0287.JPG"
         alt="Bending backwards to catch the toy"/> <figcaption>
            <p>Bending backwards to catch the toy</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>This cat is also very long. It sometimes contorts itself backwards to catch toys.</p>
<figure>
    <img src="IMG_0288.JPG"
         alt="Cat saves time by keeping its mouth open"/> <figcaption>
            <p>Cat saves time by keeping its mouth open</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>When it&rsquo;s really into the game, it just forgets to close its mouth.</p>
<p>Could this be my new icon? 🥰</p>
<figure>
    <img src="scrunchy.png"
         alt="Scrunchy"/> <figcaption>
            <p>Scrunchy</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<h3 id="angry-at-a-piece-of-plastic">Angry at a piece of plastic</h3>
<figure>
    <img src="IMG_0366.JPG"
         alt="Vampire teeth!"/> <figcaption>
            <p>Vampire teeth!</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>Not sure why but only sometimes are the cats' canines visible like this. Makes them seem evil. 🧛‍♀️</p>
<figure>
    <img src="IMG_0375.JPG"
         alt="Feline halitosis"/> <figcaption>
            <p>Feline halitosis</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>🐲 ❤️</p>
]]></content></item><item><title>Eating habits of cats</title><link>https://sjchiass.github.io/website/posts/cats/2021_w15_cats/</link><pubDate>Sun, 11 Apr 2021 19:06:43 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sjchiass.github.io/website/posts/cats/2021_w15_cats/</guid><description>My cats have a system for sharing food with one another. One also developed a way of telling us it&amp;rsquo;s finished eating. Here&amp;rsquo;s a short video showing all of these things.</description><content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Here is a video montage of our cats eating. They&rsquo;re very consistent with their habits. One always knocks on the door to be let out. Also they seem to agree how much food they leave each other.</p>
<p>(We feed them separately to control their portion sizes. Since one cat doesn&rsquo;t chew kibble, we want to encourage it to eat more wet food.)</p>

<div style="position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;">
  <iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/preyAnm5eaE" style="position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;" allowfullscreen title="YouTube Video"></iframe>
</div>

]]></content></item><item><title>The magic of bread</title><link>https://sjchiass.github.io/website/posts/food/2021_w12_food/</link><pubDate>Mon, 22 Mar 2021 20:44:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sjchiass.github.io/website/posts/food/2021_w12_food/</guid><description>I baked bread from frozen dough twice. I&amp;rsquo;ve recording both. The results are not perfect but still tasty.</description><content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2 id="background">Background</h2>
<p>I bought a 5-pack of frozen bread dough.</p>
<p>The instructions say to defrost the dough overnight in the fridge. I don&rsquo;t think I read the rest of the instructions. I added 30ml of salted butter in the pan and on top of the frozen dough.</p>
<p>Let&rsquo;s bake!</p>
<h2 id="videos-and-images">Videos and images</h2>
<h3 id="bread-1">Bread #1</h3>
<p>This is a single bread loaf in a pan.</p>

<div style="position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;">
  <iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/XTki0d15eFw" style="position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;" allowfullscreen title="YouTube Video"></iframe>
</div>

<p>Turned out okay, but not as big as I wanted.</p>
<p><img src="images/20210315_175640.jpg" alt="A diminutive loaf"></p>
<h3 id="bread-2">Bread #2</h3>
<p>Bread number 2 is in fact two breads together. The oven light was acting a bit crazy. I&rsquo;m not sure if it was the light or the webcam auto-adjusting.</p>
<p><img src="images/20210322_130818.jpg" alt="Two frozen buttered loaves"></p>

<div style="position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;">
  <iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/vOlqADRz4Is" style="position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;" allowfullscreen title="YouTube Video"></iframe>
</div>

<p>The bread(s) ended up being a bit too enormous.</p>
<p><img src="images/20210322_180310.jpg" alt="Big bread with flash"></p>
<p><img src="images/20210322_180330.jpg" alt="Big bread without flash, fork punctures visible"></p>
<h2 id="setup">Setup</h2>
<p>I put a tripod and my new webcam in front of the stove.</p>
<p>The raspberry pi I put on top of the microwave oven. I used the microwave a few times to heat my lunch, and there were no ill effects to the little computer. No doubt the wooden cutting boards absorbed the radiation.</p>
<p><img src="images/20210315_122519.jpg" alt="Camera against the oven, computer on the microwave"></p>
<p>On the raspberry pi, I ran this command to take a snapshot every minute. Each filename is timestamped.</p>
<pre><code class="language-console" data-lang="console">while sleep 60; do fswebcam -r 1920x1080 ./bread/$(date +%F%T).jpg; done
</code></pre><h2 id="making-the-videos">Making the videos</h2>
<p>The snapshots were all saved as images in the folder. I then used <code>ffmpeg</code> to make the videos.</p>
<pre><code class="language-console" data-lang="console">cat $(find . -maxdepth 1 -name &quot;*.jpg&quot; | sort -V) | ffmpeg -framerate 6 -i - -c:v libx264 -profile:v high -crf 20 -pix_fmt yuv420p bread.mp4
</code></pre><p>I used code from these two pages. The second page explained how to just use all files without having to rename them.</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://askubuntu.com/questions/610903/how-can-i-create-a-video-file-from-a-set-of-jpg-images">https://askubuntu.com/questions/610903/how-can-i-create-a-video-file-from-a-set-of-jpg-images</a></li>
<li><a href="https://askubuntu.com/questions/1183076/convert-all-the-png-files-in-a-folder-to-video">https://askubuntu.com/questions/1183076/convert-all-the-png-files-in-a-folder-to-video</a></li>
</ul>
<h2 id="cleaning-the-oven-window">Cleaning the oven window</h2>
<p>On the second run, I cleaned the oven window with baking soda and a bit of vinegar. I scrubbed vigorously with a sponge for about 10 minutes and it was all clean!</p>
]]></content></item><item><title>Weevils in my beans</title><link>https://sjchiass.github.io/website/posts/misc/2021_w12_microscope/</link><pubDate>Mon, 22 Mar 2021 19:54:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sjchiass.github.io/website/posts/misc/2021_w12_microscope/</guid><description>A few bags of pinto beans had bugs in them. I try to identify the bugs, mostly to make sure the beans are the source.</description><content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2 id="once-upon-a-time">Once upon a time</h2>
<p>Last fall I was feeling like I didn&rsquo;t want to go to the store too much, so I decided to buy a lot of long-lasting food all at once. All the dried beans I kept in a cooler.</p>
<p>(At the time I didn&rsquo;t have an easy way to cook the beans, so the purchasing decision was weird.)</p>
<p>I bought myself an Instant Pot and was really looking to make my own beans. When I got to rinsing the pinto beans, a swarm of bugs floated up in the water. (So <em>that&rsquo;s</em> why you wash and sort beans.)</p>
<p>The beans were all infested!</p>
<p>We separated everything from the cooler into separate containers. A month later, it looks like the three bags of beans were the only thing infested.</p>
<h2 id="probably-weevils">Probably weevils</h2>
<p>Ever since I bought a USB &ldquo;endoscope&rdquo; from Amazon, I&rsquo;ve been taking photos of random things. (The box box emphatically says that the endoscope is not for internal use!)</p>
<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bean_weevil">https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bean_weevil</a></p>
<p>There were quite a lot of the bugs, but a lot of them were dead. They probably weren&rsquo;t doing too well in a cold apartment with only dried beans to eat.</p>
<p><img src="images/vlcsnap-2021-02-13-17h53m27s150.png" alt="Most of them were curled on their backs"></p>
<p>I managed to put one next to a ruler and measure it to about 2mm.</p>
<p><img src="images/vlcsnap-2021-02-13-17h55m19s563.png" alt="They were only about 2mm"></p>
<p>Some of them seemed a bit dusty while others were more earthy-looking. I&rsquo;m not sure if it was the lighting or that the dead ones were dried up.</p>
<p><img src="images/vlcsnap-2021-02-13-17h59m53s473.png" alt="Curled up, different lighting"></p>
<p>There were some live ones though. I pulled one out and was able to get a good photo. They moved enough that it was hard to keep them in the frame.</p>
<p>Ferocious looking!</p>
<p><img src="images/vlcsnap-2021-02-13-18h03m02s486.png" alt="Better shot of a live one"></p>
<p>A bit of Googling makes me think that these really are weevils. The page below has a better photo than Wikipedia.</p>
<p><a href="https://bugguide.net/node/view/765912">https://bugguide.net/node/view/765912</a></p>
<p>From now on I pay <strong>much</strong> more attention to my beans!</p>
]]></content></item><item><title>Confectionery cat</title><link>https://sjchiass.github.io/website/posts/cats/2021_w12_cats/</link><pubDate>Mon, 22 Mar 2021 19:29:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sjchiass.github.io/website/posts/cats/2021_w12_cats/</guid><description>For the 2017 catlendar we dressed our cat in a confectionery costume floating in space. It&amp;rsquo;s cute.</description><content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Here is our cat in a confectionery costume. This was for the 2017 catlendar.</p>
<p><img src="images/3Mars.jpg" alt="A confectionery cat staring forward"></p>
<p>Here the cat is maybe trying to inch forward? It likes boxes.</p>
<p><img src="images/3Mars2.jpg" alt="A confectionery cat staring elsewhere"></p>
]]></content></item><item><title>2021 cat calendar</title><link>https://sjchiass.github.io/website/posts/cats/2021_w01_cats/</link><pubDate>Fri, 08 Jan 2021 13:14:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sjchiass.github.io/website/posts/cats/2021_w01_cats/</guid><description>With the lockdown we haven&amp;rsquo;t been able to distribute physical copies of our 2021 catlendar. Here&amp;rsquo;s an electronic version made with Python.</description><content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2 id="2021-cat-calendar">2021 Cat Calendar</h2>
<p>Here is the 2021 cat calendar (or &ldquo;catlendar&rdquo;).</p>
<p>I&rsquo;ve resized the images below. You can open them in a new tab to get more resolution. They&rsquo;re in US letter proportions, so you could print them to make a very basic calendar.</p>
<p>For 2022 I&rsquo;m probably going to improve the <a href="https://github.com/sjchiass/catlendar">https://github.com/sjchiass/catlendar</a> code so that you can print your own physical calendars. In order to print good calendars, the photos and calendars have to be correctly arranged so that you can fold everything.</p>
<p><img src="images/1.png" alt="January 2021"></p>
<p><img src="images/2.png" alt="February 2021"></p>
<p><img src="images/3.png" alt="March 2021"></p>
<p><img src="images/4.png" alt="April 2021"></p>
<p><img src="images/5.png" alt="May 2021"></p>
<p><img src="images/6.png" alt="June 2021"></p>
<p><img src="images/7.png" alt="July 2021"></p>
<p><img src="images/8.png" alt="August 2021"></p>
<p><img src="images/9.png" alt="September 2021"></p>
<p><img src="images/10.png" alt="October 2021"></p>
<p><img src="images/11.png" alt="November 2021"></p>
<p><img src="images/12.png" alt="December 2021"></p>
]]></content></item><item><title>Plants seem to attract gnats</title><link>https://sjchiass.github.io/website/posts/plants/2020_w48_plants/</link><pubDate>Sun, 22 Nov 2020 16:31:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sjchiass.github.io/website/posts/plants/2020_w48_plants/</guid><description>What I thought were fruit flies turn out not be.</description><content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2 id="mystery-bugs">Mystery bugs</h2>
<p>For a few weeks we&rsquo;ve been seeing small flies in the apartment. At first I thought they were dormant fruits flies reinvigorated by the warmer weather, but I noticed that they didn&rsquo;t quite look like fruit flies. They didn&rsquo;t have the large red eyes. The new bugs were also a lot easier to kill. You could slap them out of the air without them noticing. Finally, we didn&rsquo;t have fresh fruits lying around.</p>
<p>The only live plants around were the cat grass.</p>
<p><img src="images/20201119_122726.jpg" alt="Cat grass"></p>
<h3 id="identification">Identification</h3>
<p>Here are the articles for fruit flies and gnats, so that you can see some photos of what they look like.</p>
<ul>
<li>The common fruit fly <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Drosophila_melanogaster">https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Drosophila_melanogaster</a></li>
<li>The fungus gnat <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fungus_gnat">https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fungus_gnat</a> (the image below looks <em>a lot</em> like this one)</li>
</ul>
<p>Thanks to my USB microscope, I was able to get a few useful photos.</p>
<p>My first catch was one that I crushed. I kept it and brought it to my desk for photos. Since it was curled up, it was difficult to get its profile.</p>
<p><img src="images/vlcsnap-2020-11-19-10h18m30s648.png" alt="Crumpled gnat"></p>
<p>I put it up next to a ruler to show how small it is. It is 1-2mm long.</p>
<p><img src="images/20201119_121303.jpg" alt="Gnat in mms"></p>
<p>Finally I was able to catch a live one. This gnat I had only stunned, so it came back to life and stood up so that I could get a good look. It really does look like a fungus gnat.</p>
<p><img src="images/vlcsnap-2020-11-19-12h56m11s476.png" alt="Standing gnat"></p>
<p>Given these photos and the presence of the potted plants, I&rsquo;m fairly confident these are gnats.</p>
<p>Interestingly, they don&rsquo;t seem interested in my soil-free cat grass, which is still under grow lights. It may be that the strong lights made the soil dry quicker, which discouraged the gnats.</p>
<h3 id="mitigation">Mitigation</h3>
<p>The internet says that a shallow container of 50/50 water and apple cider vinegar, plus a drop of dish soap, makes a good gnat trap. The gnats are attracted to the trap and drown in it. We also found that throwing away the plants solved the problem much more quickly.</p>
<p>The trap only had the chance to catch one gnat.</p>
<p><img src="images/20201119_143553.jpg" alt="Trapped gnat"></p>
<h3 id="hypothesis">Hypothesis</h3>
<p>During the summer, I turned my microscope towards the cat grass&rsquo;s roots. I was able to find some larva crawling on it. Could these have been the gnat larvae? I&rsquo;m not especially convinced. They don&rsquo;t seem visually similar to what I find from a &ldquo;gnat larva&rdquo; image search.</p>
<p><img src="images/vlcsnap-2020-08-16-19h04m21s631.png" alt="An insect crawling on a root"></p>
]]></content></item><item><title>Review of VSI Computer Science</title><link>https://sjchiass.github.io/website/posts/misc/2020_w45_books/</link><pubDate>Sun, 01 Nov 2020 17:25:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sjchiass.github.io/website/posts/misc/2020_w45_books/</guid><description>What I learned from the book</description><content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><code>ISBN 978-0-19-873346-1</code></p>
<h3 id="general-impression">General impression</h3>
<p>I think the book was alright. I thought that the author was very good at explaining most abstract concepts, but I found his explanations of more concrete things unsatisfying. I liked his explanations of algorithms and computer engineering, but I didn&rsquo;t enjoy his talk of &ldquo;liminal artefacts&rdquo; and &ldquo;symbol processing systems&rdquo;. I&rsquo;m still not sure what these are.</p>
<p>It seems a bit like the book was better with things I already knew of, but new concepts were harder for me to understand. That said the good parts were enjoyable to read and maybe re-read.</p>
<h3 id="lesson-1-computational-thinking">Lesson 1: computational thinking</h3>
<p>The last chapter and the epilogue bring up the idea that computer science is a basic science that accesses something basic about the universe. Computers are complex systems that you can&rsquo;t really understand by studying, say, the physical properties of silicon. To understand the computers, you have to start at computer science.</p>
<p>In other words, what do you need to understand the universe? A good knowledge of mathematics and physics maybe? How would you explain computer systems without computer science? There&rsquo;s something about computer science that feels fundamental and a bit necessary, especially when you have a complex computer on your desk.</p>
<p>I think the author did a good job of setting up this argument. In the rest of the book you&rsquo;re given examples of our human intellect needing tricks to deal with computers. We can&rsquo;t really design computer hardware all on our own, for example, because it&rsquo;s too complex. So computer science is the entrance to the world of computers.</p>
<h4 id="computers-affecting-people">Computers affecting people</h4>
<p>Computers might then be teaching us fundamental skills we would not otherwise have. If you spend all day programming algorithms or designing hardware, your mental abilities change. You can start designing non-computer algorithms better, and you can better design non-computer systems. You might then have ideas that you would not have otherwise, such as approaching biology as <em>bioinformatics</em>.</p>
<p>The author brings up a good comparison with the theory of evolution. Evolution has given us a lot of other ideas.</p>
<h3 id="lesson-2-algorithms">Lesson 2: algorithms</h3>
<p>I thought that the author explained these well. Algorithms are <em>fully</em> defined procedures for getting an output out of an input. Heuristics are not fully defined and are more like reusable strategies (ex: divide and conquer). As I understood it, algorithms are more easily fed to computers; however, not all heuristics can be programmed into computers, and heuristics can be used by humans to make computers.</p>
<p>The author defines algorithms as fully-defined procedures that are self-contained and can be broken down into primitive steps. He gives the example of doing multiplication with pen and paper: if the inputs are always whole numbers, you always know what you have to do to get the output products.</p>
<h4 id="algorithm-design">Algorithm design</h4>
<p>One interesting thing that he mentions is algorithm design. I enjoy reading about things like this. When you think of a similar problem, you use analogical reasoning. By using a familiar strategy, you use heuristic reasoning. By using a formal theory in the problem domain, you use theoretical reasoning. The authors offers us a glimpse of the algorithm designers by showing us the tools of the trade.</p>
<h4 id="procedural-knowledge">Procedural knowledge</h4>
<p>Another interesting idea is that algorithms are procedural knowledge. This can be understood in two levels. The first is that &ldquo;I can learn more about something by reading its algorithm&rdquo;, so that algorithms are a source of information. The second is that &ldquo;the definition of a thing is its algorithm&rdquo;, so that the algorithm is how you see the thing itself. How do you define multiplication? Well, here&rsquo;s how you multiply two numbers with pen and paper.</p>
<h3 id="lesson-3-heuristics">Lesson 3: heuristics</h3>
<p>Heuristics are explained in the later chapters. Unlike algorithms, we do not know heuristics as fully-defined procedures. Rather, we know heuristics as general solutions or strategies. While algorithms are single solutions to single problems, heuristics are malleable solutions to varied problems.</p>
<p>The author helps us understand heuristics by making us think of their use outside of computers. For example, I know that I use heuristics for putting the dishes away. I start with the items that can be removed without making others fall. I also tend to favour larger and heavier items first. At some arbitrary point I decide to put away the utensils.</p>
<p>An example of a well-known heuristic is divide-and-conquer.</p>
<p>Heuristics are very general but can still be used with computers. The heuristic may be better than an algorithm when the algorithms are too costly, the algorithms don&rsquo;t exist, or we don&rsquo;t sufficiently understand the problem we&rsquo;re trying to solve. In these cases, heuristics can provide the solution.</p>
<h4 id="satisficing">Satisficing</h4>
<p><em>Satisficing</em> is how the author describes imperfect solutions still end up being satisfactory. Rather than coming up with a perfect algorithmic solution, you can come up with a satisfactory heuristic solution instead. For example, how would you design a chess-playing computer program? Rather than solving the game of chess completely, the author says, you can give the human player a moderate challenge by using <em>satisficing</em> solution.</p>
<h3 id="tidbits">Tidbits</h3>
<p>Computer programs are <em>liminal</em> artefacts that are algorithms written in computer languages.</p>
<p>Computer architecture refers both to the &ldquo;inner&rdquo; physical architecture of the circuitry and the &ldquo;outer&rdquo; architecture of the instruction set.</p>
<h3 id="final-thoughts">Final thoughts</h3>
<p>I wonder how much of this book I&rsquo;ll remember. I&rsquo;ll probably think of it when I hear about algorithms and heuristics. When I hear about computer science I might now recall &ldquo;computational thinking&rdquo;.</p>
]]></content></item><item><title>Physical play/pause button for your phone</title><link>https://sjchiass.github.io/website/posts/electronics/2020_w44_electronics/</link><pubDate>Sun, 25 Oct 2020 14:57:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sjchiass.github.io/website/posts/electronics/2020_w44_electronics/</guid><description>Making a phone play/pause button: conveniently pause your podcasts when someone is talking to you.</description><content type="html"><![CDATA[<h3 id="basic-idea">Basic idea</h3>
<p>You can tell your phone to play/pause/hang-up by sending signals through the microphone. It&rsquo;s as simple as shorting the microphone to ground. It is also possible to have buttons to increase/decrease volume. This function is integrated into headsets and headphones+mic combos.</p>
<p>Here&rsquo;s a demo of this. (I can&rsquo;t seem to record any audio, so all my videos are muted.)</p>

<div style="position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;">
  <iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/wom0aqp9hkI" style="position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;" allowfullscreen title="YouTube Video"></iframe>
</div>

<p><img src="images/20201024_141750.jpg" alt="Button board"></p>
<p>The voltage level signals are defined by resistor values, all explained here: <a href="https://source.android.com/devices/accessories/headset/plug-headset-spec">https://source.android.com/devices/accessories/headset/plug-headset-spec</a></p>
<p>If all you want is the play/pause, then all you need to do is find a way to short the microphone.</p>
<h3 id="what-you-need">What you need</h3>
<p>I&rsquo;m assuming most people will have a pair of headphones that they like and they just want to add a button to it.</p>
<p>I think the best idea then is to get a microphone/headphone splitter. You can plug in your headphones and then you just need to plug in your contraption into the microphone half of it.</p>
<p><img src="images/20201025_170156.jpg" alt="3.5mm Y splitter"></p>
<p>The black connector goes into the phone, the green receptacle is for the headphones (out), and the pink receptacle is for the microphone (in).</p>
<p>You will also need one or more sacrificial headphone connectors. It&rsquo;s much easier to work with the wires still intact: soldering directly to the connector can be a challenge.</p>
<p><img src="images/20201025_172425.jpg" alt="A salvaged 3.5mm connector"></p>
<h3 id="information-on-the-35mm-jack">Information on the 3.5mm jack</h3>
<p>I think we all know this type of connector as the standard headphone jack. Walkmans, computers, and phones all use it.</p>
<p>Below I have three examples of it. The shape is generally the same, but the number of pins/connections varies. The separate connections are the bands separated by the black/green plastic. The ground is always the closest band to the rest of the plug, the part in rubber or solid plastic.</p>
<p><img src="images/20201025_171027.jpg" alt="Three types of 3.5mm connectors"></p>
<p>The top connector with 4 connections is from my Y splitter. It&rsquo;s also used for headphones with an integrated microphone. The connector can carry (from left to right) the L+R stereo signal, the microphone signal, and the ground; a total of 4 connections.</p>
<p>The middle connector is just a standard headphone jack. It has L+R stereo and the ground. This is the kind of 3.5mm jack you usually see.</p>
<p>The bottom connector is from a microphone/speaker you can clip somewhere. It only has two connections, so you would need to push a button to talk, like a walkie-talkie.</p>
<h3 id="dont-melt-the-35mm-jack">Don&rsquo;t melt the 3.5mm jack!</h3>
<p>The 3.5mm connector itself uses plastic to separate the connections. The ones I&rsquo;ve taken apart had large blobs of lead solder to connect the wires. If you&rsquo;re not quick, you can easily melt the plastic and ruin the connector.</p>
<p>The connector below had its insides melted from me applying 450C+ heat for 10+ seconds. The microphone is now permanently shorted to ground.</p>
<p><img src="images/20201025_172740.jpg" alt="A look at the bare connector"></p>
<h3 id="pesky-little-headphone-wires">Pesky little headphone wires</h3>
<p>Headphone wires are very fine in order to be nice and flexible. They come with a coating that will block electric current. With my multimeter on continuity mode, I can only get a connection at the tips of the cut wires; the lengths of the wires are all well-isolated.</p>
<p>This makes them annoying to work with. Unlike bigger wires, you can&rsquo;t just strip off the insulation and splice them wherever you want. You also have to be careful when soldering since you can destroy them by pressing a dry iron tip to them.</p>
<p>Below you can see an example of this tiny coated wire. Both the signal wire and the ground wire are together in the same housing, so they need the coating for the headphones to work properly.</p>
<p><img src="images/vlcsnap-2020-10-18-19h15m47s581_blue_wire.png" alt="Some coated wire"></p>
<p><img src="images/vlcsnap-2020-10-25-14h12m08s748.png" alt="The pair of wires"></p>
<p>You might be tempted to burn it all off with a lighter, but it makes a mess. There may end up being too much charred junk to make a good connection.</p>
<p><img src="images/vlcsnap-2020-10-18-19h20m04s184_burnt_blue.png" alt="Some burnt wire"></p>
<p>It turns out one trick is to dip the wire into molten solder. This burns off the coating while also replacing it with a tin/lead coating. I just set a big blob of tin solder at 450C and run the wire through it.</p>
<p>Here is me doing the bluish coated wire. (With audio you could hear the sizzle!)</p>

<div style="position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;">
  <iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/exewnoKt3lk" style="position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;" allowfullscreen title="YouTube Video"></iframe>
</div>

<p>Here&rsquo;s the clear/nylon wire (the ground) with the solder getting a bit dirty.</p>

<div style="position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;">
  <iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/SCDMct3pVyc" style="position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;" allowfullscreen title="YouTube Video"></iframe>
</div>

<p>After this, you end up with some partially-tinned wires that are easier to work with.</p>
<h3 id="testing-out-some-resistor-values">Testing out some resistor values</h3>
<p>I assume you now have a 3.5mm connector with some nice sturdy hook-up wires. I used 22 AWG solid-core since it&rsquo;s great for breadboards.</p>
<p>Before you settle on your permanent board, it&rsquo;s a good idea to make sure you can get it all working on something non-permanent.</p>
<p>If you&rsquo;re interested in play/pause only, you just need to short the microphone. If you want to change the volume, 220 ohm and 470 ohm resistors should be a good start.</p>
<p>You can test these on a breadboard with a button. Keep pressing the button and see what happens to your phone. As you test different values, write down their effects.</p>
<p><img src="images/20201023_190024.jpg" alt="A simple prototype"></p>
<h3 id="soldering-everything-to-protoboard">Soldering everything to protoboard</h3>
<p>I learned two things:</p>
<ul>
<li>Clean the copper pads first. If it&rsquo;s old stuff from the back of the drawer, it&rsquo;ll have oxidized.</li>
<li>Give yourself some room to place the components. Don&rsquo;t just cut the protoboard to <em>exactly</em> the size you need to fit the buttons.</li>
</ul>
<p>The solder didn&rsquo;t really stick to the pads. I just kept applying more until the thing seemed like it would hold together. I might as well have used cardboard&hellip;</p>
<p><img src="images/vlcsnap-2020-10-24-11h20m53s678.png" alt="Solder resting on top of the pads"></p>
<p>Everything went okay, but I ended up with a cramped board. I really like these buttons; I forgot about everything else.</p>
<p>I put a 5k ohm resistor across the MIC and GND since I figured the phone might expect it. (This is a value from the Android documentation.) The phone may need a small current to keep passing through the microphone or otherwise it won&rsquo;t be aware of its existence.</p>
<p>The circuit is nearly identical to the one from the documentation, except that my resistor values are slightly different and ordered differently: <a href="https://source.android.com/devices/accessories/headset/plug-headset-spec">https://source.android.com/devices/accessories/headset/plug-headset-spec</a></p>
<p><img src="images/20201024_141804.jpg" alt="Back of the board"></p>
<h3 id="lessons-learned">Lessons learned</h3>
<p>The board works poorly. The play/pause button and the volume-down button work, but the volume-up button almost always fails.</p>
<p>I suspect that there&rsquo;s something not right with the buttons. It could also be that the phone expects cleaner signals that I&rsquo;m generating.</p>
<p>I wonder&hellip; how does this specification work alongside a real microphone? When someone uses the button on a phone call, is there any noise added to the audio?</p>
]]></content></item><item><title>Graceful cat flop</title><link>https://sjchiass.github.io/website/posts/cats/2020_w40_cats/</link><pubDate>Sun, 27 Sep 2020 15:11:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sjchiass.github.io/website/posts/cats/2020_w40_cats/</guid><description>A photo gallery of a cat in laying on its back.</description><content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2 id="scandal">Scandal!</h2>
<p>Here is my cat lying halfway on its back.</p>
<p><img src="images/20200927_125519.jpg" alt="Cat on its back"></p>
<p>Here is the same position from the front. The cat seems to be relaxing.</p>
<p><img src="images/20200927_125530.jpg" alt="Cat on its back, face-to-face"></p>
<p>Here is the cat from behind. It looks pretty comfortable.</p>
<p><img src="images/20200927_125541.jpg" alt="The mysteries of feline rest"></p>
]]></content></item><item><title>New cat grass supplies</title><link>https://sjchiass.github.io/website/posts/plants/2020_w40_plants/</link><pubDate>Sun, 27 Sep 2020 14:55:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sjchiass.github.io/website/posts/plants/2020_w40_plants/</guid><description>Got grow lights, soilless media, and fed cats some grass</description><content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2 id="the-new-supplies">The new supplies</h2>
<p>I got vermiculite and peat moss from the store. Vermiculite is a very light material that&rsquo;s made by heating a mineral and expanding it. It&rsquo;s used in hydroponics as a growing medium. Peat moss is a growing soil additive that helps retain water (I&rsquo;m thinking of mixing it with the vermiculite).</p>
<p>The bag of vermiculite sounds like a bag of cat food, so the cats are very interested in it.</p>
<p><img src="images/20200925_120907.jpg" alt="Cats investigating vermiculite"></p>
<p>The grow lights I got are very similar to the LED spotlights I&rsquo;ve been using. They use 8.5W compared to 11W for the previous spotlights.</p>
<p>They look pretty orange rather than the pink I was expecting. These lights may be intended for flowering plants, so it will be interesting to see what they do for the non-flowering cat grass.</p>
<p><img src="images/20200926_144253.jpg" alt="The hue of the light"></p>
<p>Here is what the box says about its colour spectrum. A lot of the light is reddish.</p>
<p><img src="images/20200927_143944.jpg" alt="Box"></p>
<h2 id="cats-love-the-grass">Cats love the grass</h2>
<p>The cats adore the grass. If they hear you cutting some of it, they&rsquo;ll come running and meowing to eat it.</p>
<p>They will even paw at it aggressively. They&rsquo;re usually nice babbys! Why does the grass make them evil?</p>
<p><img src="images/20200927_140936.jpg" alt="Cat pawing for the grass"></p>
<p>They eat it like an inkjet printer slowly pulls in a sheet of paper. They very loudly chew the grass, and slowly the grass disappears down to their stomachs, step by step.</p>
<p><img src="images/20200927_140949.jpg" alt="Cat chewing the grass"></p>
]]></content></item><item><title>Quinoa-stuffed peppers</title><link>https://sjchiass.github.io/website/posts/food/2020_w40_food/</link><pubDate>Sun, 27 Sep 2020 14:45:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sjchiass.github.io/website/posts/food/2020_w40_food/</guid><description>Easy stuffed peppers in an air fryer</description><content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2 id="pretty-easy-to-make-stuffed-peppers">Pretty easy to make stuffed peppers</h2>
<p>The air fryer was able to roast the outside of the peppers while getting the insides <em>very hot</em>.</p>
<p>Even better: minimal cleanup!</p>
<h3 id="ingredients">Ingredients</h3>
<ul>
<li>Leftover quinoa</li>
<li>Large peppers
<ul>
<li>Here we cut the tops off</li>
<li>You can slice them in halves, making scoops/boats</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Salsa to mix into the quinoa</li>
<li>Cheese as a topping</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="procedure">Procedure</h3>
<ul>
<li>Prepare the peppers</li>
<li>Mix the quinoa with the salsa in a bowl (this is the stuffing)</li>
<li>Stuff the peppers</li>
<li>Top the stuffed peppers with the cheese</li>
<li>Air-fry for
<ul>
<li>12 minutes at 350F for well-cooked</li>
<li>20 minutes at 550F for nicely roasted</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Let cool for at least 10 minutes</li>
</ul>
<p>It&rsquo;s best to leave a lot of room for the air to circulate.</p>
<p><img src="images/20200915_182248.jpg" alt="Raw peppers"></p>
<p>After 10 minutes things have gotten hot.</p>
<p><img src="images/20200915_183222.jpg" alt="After 10 minutes at 350F"></p>
<p>After 20 minutes, the peppers have started to roast on the outside. There is a clearer photo below.</p>
<p><img src="images/20200915_184237.jpg" alt="After 20 minutes at 350F"></p>
<p>You can see how the skin of the pepper has roasted.</p>
<p><img src="images/20200915_184458.jpg" alt="Nicely roasted peppers"></p>
]]></content></item><item><title>Getting back into electronics</title><link>https://sjchiass.github.io/website/posts/electronics/2020_w38_electronics/</link><pubDate>Sun, 13 Sep 2020 20:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sjchiass.github.io/website/posts/electronics/2020_w38_electronics/</guid><description>Getting back into eletronics again after a hiatus, fun with Arduinos.</description><content type="html"><![CDATA[<h3 id="past-week">Past week</h3>
<h4 id="the-updated-workspace">The updated workspace</h4>
<p>Last week I set up a workspace to program an Arduino on a breadboard. I&rsquo;ve attached the monitor to an arm to give more space. Originally, the monitor was higher up, but I found that I didn&rsquo;t like having to crane my head upwards.</p>
<p><img src="images/20200913_193838.jpg" alt="Setup"></p>
<h4 id="the-arduino-oscilloscope">The Arduino oscilloscope</h4>
<p>At this point I have more of a voltage logger than a functional oscilloscope. Yet even this is valuable because I can see changes in voltage a lot better than with a multimeter.</p>
<p>The circuit is the same as in the matchbox oscilloscope guide: <a href="https://www.instructables.com/id/Oscilloscope-in-a-Matchbox-Arduino/">https://www.instructables.com/id/Oscilloscope-in-a-Matchbox-Arduino/</a></p>
<p><img src="images/20200913_193441.jpg" alt="Breadboard circuit"></p>
<p>The 100nF caramic capacitors turned out to be important. Using nicer-looking mylar capacitors (in beautiful green) gave worse signals. Ceramics are better than mylar (polyester) for these things. (I wish I could find a use for these beautiful green capacitors.)</p>
<p>The test signal comes from a 555 timer, so it&rsquo;s a square wave.</p>
<p>At first the signals weren&rsquo;t read properly. It turned out that I wasn&rsquo;t properly reading the serial data in Python. If I missed a byte, the values would drop by a lot (ex: 1010 &ndash;&gt; 010).</p>
<p><img src="images/animation.gif" alt="Buggy signal"></p>
<p>I cleaned up my Python code by decoding the serial data, splitting it by newlines, and only keeping numbers that are complete 4-character records.</p>
<pre><code># Read the Arduino's Serial.println()
# The Arduino pads the integers with leading 0s so that they're always
# 4 characters wide
x1 = ard.read(ard.inWaiting()).decode(&quot;ascii&quot;)
x1 = [(5.0 * int(x) / 1023.0) for x in x1.split(&quot;\r\n&quot;) if len(x) == 4]
</code></pre><p>The results are now clean.</p>
<p><img src="images/animation_better.gif" alt="Square-wave graph"></p>
<p>The circuit can also read from a capacitor-bypassed signal. The 0-5V measure above is instead pushed through a 200nF capacitor and adjusted to a range of 0V to 1.1V. This bypassed signal is interpreted at -0.55V and +0.55V.</p>
<p>You can see the effect of the capacitor on the signal. The square wave has rounded edges. I think this measurement mode would be better with faster and finer signals, such as fast-acting digital ICs.</p>
<p><img src="images/animation_ac.gif" alt="Square-wave through a capacitor"></p>
<h4 id="fun-with-banana-plugs">Fun with banana plugs</h4>
<p>I got some &ldquo;cheap&rdquo; banana plugs on Amazon for $16. The reviews for these were bad, but I really wanted banana plugs; ANY BANANA PLUGS!</p>
<p>They came in a nice box, with free screwdriver and wrench. Oh, there are also binding posts in there, but I&rsquo;m not sure if I&rsquo;ll use them.</p>
<p><img src="images/20200911_132245.jpg" alt="Box of red and black plugs"></p>
<p>The reviews warned that it was difficult to solder the plugs, but I found that an iron at 450C with lead-free solder did the trick. I used primary wire for the wires, which is 18-gauge stranded copper. I reinforced the plugs with three layers of heat-shrink tubing (very nice!).</p>
<p><img src="images/20200911_132211.jpg" alt="Completed banana plugs"></p>
<h4 id="a-new-breadboard">A new breadboard</h4>
<p>I bought this &ldquo;de luxe&rdquo; breadboard: <a href="https://www.buyapi.ca/product/large-solderless-breadboard/">https://www.buyapi.ca/product/large-solderless-breadboard/</a></p>
<p>For some reason I thought the binding posts were connected to the breadboard (like through some internal circuit). Instead you need to wire the binding posts to the breadboard power rails.</p>
<p><img src="images/20200908_193518.jpg" alt="A new large breadboard"></p>
<p>Also, the rubber feet had useless glue, which is what some reviews complained about. The solution: use superglue (cyanoacrylate). The superglue glued the rubber feet perfectly.</p>
<p><img src="images/20200908_203030.jpg" alt="Sub-par rubber feet"></p>
<h3 id="next-week">Next week</h3>
<p>I&rsquo;m going to keep playing with my homemade voltage logger. There are a few things to do.</p>
<ol>
<li>Add some kind of interface to navigate the data.</li>
<li>Look at how real oscilloscopes are used.</li>
<li>Create better test data, such as faster-acting circuit.</li>
</ol>
<p>I shouldn&rsquo;t forget to wrap up my <code>pitemp</code> project: <a href="https://github.com/sjchiass/pitemp">https://github.com/sjchiass/pitemp</a></p>
]]></content></item><item><title>My continued eggplant obsession</title><link>https://sjchiass.github.io/website/posts/food/2020_w38_food/</link><pubDate>Sun, 13 Sep 2020 19:49:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sjchiass.github.io/website/posts/food/2020_w38_food/</guid><description>Air frying eggplants vs. pan frying them</description><content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This week we got two large eggplants. One went into the air fryer and the other into the frying pan.</p>
<p>I think that egplants need humidity to soften and cook. I now wonder how to reliably make good air-fried eggplants. Should I soak the eggplant in marinade?</p>
<h4 id="air-fried-eggplant">Air-fried eggplant</h4>
<p>Last week the air fryer had made very dry eggplant chips (with chewy skin). This time I cut it into larger 1&quot; cubes.</p>
<p>I air fried the cubes at 350F for 36 minutes, and they unfortunately burned. They may look delicious, but they tasted burnt.</p>
<p><img src="images/20200908_180141.jpg" alt="Burnt eggplants"></p>
<h4 id="pan-fried-eggplant">Pan-fried eggplant</h4>
<p>This was a recipe with soy sauce, sesame oil, honey, and cayenne pepper flakes. The sauce was only added at the end, after the eggplant had cooked on medium-high for 15 minutes.</p>
<p>I think the extra humidity here is what helped the eggplant to cook better.</p>
<p><img src="images/20200908_180151.jpg" alt="Softer fried eggplant"></p>
]]></content></item><item><title>A bird tries to eat a sleeping cat</title><link>https://sjchiass.github.io/website/posts/cats/2020_w38_cats/</link><pubDate>Sun, 13 Sep 2020 19:43:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sjchiass.github.io/website/posts/cats/2020_w38_cats/</guid><description>A bird of prey tried to eat my cat but crashed against the window instead. I tried to identify it, but I&amp;rsquo;m not sure.</description><content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2 id="poor-babbys">Poor babbys</h2>
<p>Here is my cat sleeping on the couch. It&rsquo;s the same place the other cat was sleeping last week.</p>
<p><img src="images/20200908_123137.jpg" alt="Cat on the couch"></p>
<h3 id="drama">Drama!</h3>
<p>The other cat was sleeping in the cat tree when a bird tried to eat it! The large bird hit the window glass and then went on the edge of the balcony.</p>
<p>It appears to have been a merlin. According to Wikipedia, merlins can be about a foot long, so this might have been a slightly bigger one. The tail matches the pictures.</p>
<p><img src="images/20200913_125856.jpg" alt="Bird of prey on the balcony edge"></p>
]]></content></item><item><title>Trying to make my grass flower</title><link>https://sjchiass.github.io/website/posts/plants/2020_w37_plants/</link><pubDate>Sun, 06 Sep 2020 16:40:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sjchiass.github.io/website/posts/plants/2020_w37_plants/</guid><description>Worth a try</description><content type="html"><![CDATA[<h3 id="past-week">Past week</h3>
<p>I changed the light from a daylight spotlight to a warm-white bulb. I also reduced the light time from 18 hours to 12 hours.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;m hoping that the change in light will make the plants flower. Plants often do this in response to shortening days. It&rsquo;s called &ldquo;bolting&rdquo;. You&rsquo;ve likely seen it happen if you&rsquo;ve grown lettuce: the plant stops growing tasty leaves and instead makes a long bitter stem (and perhaps yellow flowers).</p>
<p>Some of the grass is getting a lot longer, so it may be working. One of my cats has started meowing at it (the plant is on top of a bookcase, out of reach).</p>
<p><img src="images/20200905_122508.jpg" alt="Long grass"></p>
<h3 id="next-week">Next week</h3>
<p>Some of the grass seems to be burning at the tips. This might be from a lack of nutrients. I&rsquo;ve started adding a bit of fertilizer to the water.</p>
<p>It looks like the hardware store sells decent-looking LED grow lights, so I might pick up a bulb to tests its effectiveness. The grow bulbs on Amazon look terrible. There are enough critical reviews to make me suspicious.</p>
<p>(After reading this article, I&rsquo;ve started doubting the &ldquo;top&rdquo; reviewers: <a href="https://arstechnica.com/gadgets/2020/09/amazons-top-uk-reviewers-appear-to-profit-from-fake-5-star-posts/">https://arstechnica.com/gadgets/2020/09/amazons-top-uk-reviewers-appear-to-profit-from-fake-5-star-posts/</a>)</p>
<p>If I were to get the bulb, I would put two pots next to each other separated by a partition. One pot would get a normal daylight spotlight, the other would get a grow light. Which will grow faster?</p>
<p>The store also sells perlite, vermiculite, and peat. If I can cobble together a hypdroponics system (probably nutrient film?), I could have some fun playing with that. I am not sure where to find tubing for my miniature pumps.</p>
]]></content></item><item><title>Air frying eggplants and bologna</title><link>https://sjchiass.github.io/website/posts/food/2020_w37_food/</link><pubDate>Sun, 06 Sep 2020 16:26:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sjchiass.github.io/website/posts/food/2020_w37_food/</guid><description>Air frying eggplants and bologna: not great</description><content type="html"><![CDATA[<h3 id="eggplant-chips">Eggplant chips</h3>
<p>These cooked well but weren&rsquo;t that great. The eggplant skin was chewy (but no doubt full of fiber). I think this would have been great with some of the skin peeled off.</p>
<p>I started with three Asian eggplants. I cut them all up in 5mm thick disks.</p>
<p><img src="images/20200831_172629.jpg" alt="Local eggplant"></p>
<p>There was enough eggplant to fill the XXL air fryer.</p>
<p><img src="images/20200831_173115.jpg" alt="Raw eggplant chips"></p>
<p>I cooked the eggplant for 35 minutes at 350F, tossing every 10 minutes. Yeah, it took a while.</p>
<p><img src="images/20200831_181057.jpg" alt="Eggplant chips"></p>
<p>Despite the chewy skin, this was still a feel-good dish. It didn&rsquo;t taste particularly good, but I felt like I gave my jaw muscles a good workout.</p>
<h3 id="fried-bologna">Fried bologna</h3>
<p>I fried some pork-chicken bologna. It was &ldquo;Blue Ribbon&rdquo; quality according to the packaging. I may have eaten bologna royalty.</p>
<p>It took 30 minutes at 350F to fry it all. Unfortunately, it&rsquo;s not something that fries well in an air fryer. It&rsquo;s a catch-22. If you spread them out, you create a meat barrier that blocks the airflow. If you toss them around, the slices cover eat other and won&rsquo;t crisp.</p>
<p>Final impression: tastes like hotdogs.</p>
<p><img src="images/20200902_190953.jpg" alt="Bologna chips"></p>
]]></content></item><item><title>Preparing an Arduino workspace</title><link>https://sjchiass.github.io/website/posts/electronics/2020_w37_electronics/</link><pubDate>Sun, 06 Sep 2020 16:12:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sjchiass.github.io/website/posts/electronics/2020_w37_electronics/</guid><description>Preparing an Arduino workspace. Nice to have everything together.</description><content type="html"><![CDATA[<h3 id="past-week">Past week</h3>
<p>I am really interested in building some kind of Arduino oscilloscope. This requires a nice workplace for the Arduino but also a computer nearby for programming it. I was able to fit a 24&quot; monitor onto my little desk.</p>
<p><img src="images/20200905_115309.jpg" alt="Setup"></p>
<p>The desk is an <a href="https://www.ikea.com/ca/en/p/brusali-desk-brown-30302299/">Ikea Brusali</a>, so 90x52cm.</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s not that bad since most of the work is done on a breadboard. A good pair of tweezers can pick up things when space is tight. If I were soldering, I&rsquo;d be banging my arms everywhere.</p>
<h3 id="next-week">Next week</h3>
<p>I&rsquo;ve ordered a few things to help me out.</p>
<p>An HDMI to VGA adapter will let me use a smaller VGA monitor with the Raspberry Pi, freeing up some space.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;m also getting a bigger breadboard with binding post power connectors. The board can have two independant power supplies, which is important if I want the oscilloscope circuit to measure a separate circuit that oscillates. I need the Arduino&rsquo;s power supply to be clean.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;m also getting variety packs of capacitors. I&rsquo;m hoping to be able to convert the square wave of a 555 timer into a sine wave. And of course I&rsquo;ll only know this has worked if I have a homemade oscilloscope to measure it.</p>
]]></content></item><item><title>Cat relaxing in a funny pose</title><link>https://sjchiass.github.io/website/posts/cats/2020_w37_cats/</link><pubDate>Sun, 06 Sep 2020 16:09:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sjchiass.github.io/website/posts/cats/2020_w37_cats/</guid><description>A cat sleeping in a way that makes it look like it&amp;rsquo;s walking.</description><content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2 id="cat-relaxing-in-bipedal-mode">Cat relaxing in bipedal mode</h2>
<p><img src="images/20200831_165114.jpg" alt="Cat on the couch"></p>
]]></content></item><item><title>A basic voltmeter with an LCD</title><link>https://sjchiass.github.io/website/posts/electronics/2020_w36_electronics/</link><pubDate>Sun, 30 Aug 2020 16:46:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sjchiass.github.io/website/posts/electronics/2020_w36_electronics/</guid><description>A basic voltmeter with an LCD. Simple but instructive.</description><content type="html"><![CDATA[<h3 id="past-week">Past week</h3>
<p>You can do fun things by reading the Arduino analog pins.</p>
<p>I used this sample LCD code as a base: <a href="https://www.arduino.cc/en/Tutorial/HelloWorld">https://www.arduino.cc/en/Tutorial/HelloWorld</a>.</p>
<p>The Arduino (the Atmega 328P) measures 0V-5V on its analog pins. It can return 1024 values (10-bit). By default the reference is the voltage supply (5V) but can be switched to whatever you have connected to the <code>AREF</code> pin.</p>
<p>So out of the box you can make a 0V-5V voltmeter with the analog pins. Feed the analog pin a voltage and it&rsquo;ll return a number from 0 to 1023. Divide the number by 5 and you get a float from 0V to ~5V.</p>
<p>With voltage dividers you can expand that range. By dividing your input with 110k ohms (ground) and 460k ohms (voltage), you will divide your incoming voltage by 5.7. If you feed in 20V, it will become about 3.5V, which is within the 0V-5V range. Your range has now expanded to 0V-28V.</p>
<p>So with a voltage divider you can make a basic voltmeter that measure beyond the 0V to 5V range. Here&rsquo;s how I did it in the Arduino C code.</p>
<pre><code>// print the calculated voltage
float vin = 5.05; // should this be 5V instead?
// divide resistances by 1000 for simplicity
float adj = (101.0 + 476.0) / 101.0;
lcd.print(vin * analogRead(A0) * adj / 1024.0);
</code></pre><p>The higher voltage is a bit too high.</p>
<p><img src="images/20200830_144555.jpg" alt="Measuring higher voltage"></p>
<p>The lower voltage is better, I think?</p>
<p><img src="images/20200830_144601.jpg" alt="Measuring lower voltage"></p>
<p>Just to show my setup, I had the variable voltage of my power supply going into the voltage divider and then into the analog pin. The rest of the circuit follows the LCD guide and is powered by the power supply&rsquo;s regulated 5V, which in turn is the <code>AREF</code>.</p>
<p><img src="images/20200830_144633.jpg" alt="Setup"></p>
<h3 id="next-week">Next week</h3>
<p>Here is a plot of the squishing that happens with my voltage divider above. The divider reduces the higher voltage into the 0V to 5V suitable for the Arduino analog pin.</p>
<p><img src="images/simple_divider.png" alt="Simple divider"></p>
<p>When you divide with ground (0V), you&rsquo;re using it to reduce the voltage of the incoming positive voltage source (allowing you to measure higher voltages). The re-scaling of the voltage is centered on 0V.</p>
<p>If you were to divide with another voltage, it would be centered on that instead. Or rather, it would be centered more towards it.</p>
<p><img src="images/5v_divider.png" alt="5V divider"></p>
<p>It took me a bit of time to realize that this is how voltage dividers behave with two positive voltage sources.</p>
<p>If I want to offset a voltage, I have to use the Arduino&rsquo;s <code>AREF</code>. I need to think more about how the reference value affects things. The range should always be 0V to <code>AREF</code>, right? How can it be made to be below 0V?</p>
]]></content></item><item><title>Measuring soil humidity with an ohmmeter</title><link>https://sjchiass.github.io/website/posts/plants/2020_w36_plants/</link><pubDate>Sun, 30 Aug 2020 16:34:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sjchiass.github.io/website/posts/plants/2020_w36_plants/</guid><description>A simple test</description><content type="html"><![CDATA[<h3 id="past-week">Past week</h3>
<p>The grass has been getting stronger! After removing the CD case, lowering the container 2-3 inches, the grass once again reaches the light!</p>
<p><img src="images/20200830_150702.jpg" alt="Two weeks of growth"></p>
<p>During the week I realized that soil humidity meters work by measuring resistance. Damp soil conducts electricity better, while dry soil conducts poorly.</p>
<p>The soil moisture sensors work by feeding voltage to their prongs, and they return a variable voltage. My multimeter effectively does the same thing when it measure resistances, so it should work too.</p>
<p>I measure the resistance with the soil dry. I get 10M ohms, which is quite a lot. (To be fair, I expected infinite resistance.)</p>
<p><img src="images/20200827_084642.jpg" alt="Dry soil resistance"></p>
<p>After I poured water into the container and got it nice and wet, the resistance was now 186k ohms, 1/60th the ohms of the dry soil. Again, I expected higher resistance with the probes being two inches apart. Electricity must conduct well in wet soil full of minerals and the like.</p>
<p><img src="images/20200827_084945.jpg" alt="Dry soil resistance"></p>
<h3 id="next-week">Next week</h3>
<p>I desoldered the header pins from my Raspberry Pi Zero, so I could use it as a camera. The case won&rsquo;t close with the headers facing up. Darn!</p>
<p><img src="images/20200830_161819.jpg" alt="Pi Zero camera"></p>
<p>The soldering was tough. I tried removing all of the solder with a solder sucker and solder wick. I put the pi in a breadboard to dissipate a bit of heat. All the wicking and sucking wasn&rsquo;t enough to separate the headers: the GPIO has a lot of pins so it&rsquo;s quite the task&hellip;</p>
<p><img src="images/20200823_184219.jpg" alt="Desoldering the headers"></p>
<p>I ended up securing the pi, and I pulled out the pins one-by-one by heating them on one side and pulling them out with pliers. When the solder melted, the pins slid right out. Messy but effective.</p>
<p>Below you can see how there&rsquo;s a bit of solder left over. There&rsquo;s gunk everywhere. Could it be cleaned with alcohol?</p>
<p><img src="images/vlcsnap-2020-08-30-16h22m23s591.png" alt="Close-up of the GPIO"></p>
<p>The Pi still works though.</p>
]]></content></item><item><title>Various cat pictures</title><link>https://sjchiass.github.io/website/posts/cats/2020_w36_cats/</link><pubDate>Sun, 30 Aug 2020 15:52:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sjchiass.github.io/website/posts/cats/2020_w36_cats/</guid><description>I took photos of my cats sleeping and sneaking under the couch.</description><content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2 id="cats-in-various-states-of-rest">Cats in various states of rest</h2>
<p>The cats love sleeping on my meditation cushion. The cushion happens to be the right size for them, so they can bundle up on it and relax.</p>
<p><img src="images/20200827_132512.jpg" alt="Meditating cat"></p>
<p>This morning my cat came to see me and decided to sleep on the chair. The cat overflows the edge because it&rsquo;s sleeping on its side.</p>
<p><img src="images/20200830_083218.jpg" alt="Cat sprawl"></p>
<p>I found the two cats sleeping close to each other. This happens rarely. It may be that the green blanket has put a barrier between them and has prevented feline strife.</p>
<p><img src="images/20200830_135345.jpg" alt="The cats agree to nap in peace"></p>
<p>Here are two photos of the cat sneaking underneath the couch.</p>
<p><img src="images/20200825_083929.jpg" alt="Couch cat A"></p>
<p><img src="images/20200825_083947.jpg" alt="Couch cat B"></p>
]]></content></item><item><title>Various air fryer dishes</title><link>https://sjchiass.github.io/website/posts/food/2020_w36_food/</link><pubDate>Sun, 30 Aug 2020 15:35:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sjchiass.github.io/website/posts/food/2020_w36_food/</guid><description>Cooking many bits evenly</description><content type="html"><![CDATA[<h3 id="past-week">Past week</h3>
<h4 id="eggplant-wraps">Eggplant wraps</h4>
<p>We had three Italian/Sicilian eggplants. I cubed two and put them in the air fryer, and the other one I sliced and pan fried. I also air fryer some bell peppers with onions. Everything going into the air fryer was coated in peanut oil, and the frying pan eggplants were fried in olive oil.</p>
<p><img src="images/20200825_184412.jpg" alt="Wrap ingredients"></p>
<ul>
<li>Air fry cubed eggplants 30 minutes at 350F; keep covered and warm in oven at 200F</li>
<li>Air fry peppers and onions 12 minutes at 400F; keep covered and warm in oven at 200F</li>
<li>Pan fry sliced eggplant at medium heat for a long time (not satisfied)</li>
</ul>
<p>The cubed eggplants I tossed in peanut oil and premade chili seasoning (the kind of spice mix that comes with a chili recipe in the back). I cooked these cubes for 30 minutes at 350F in the air fryer. I frequently checked and tossed them to make sure they were alright.</p>
<p>By the end, the air-fried eggplant cubes had lost most of their moisture and were delicious!</p>
<p>The peppers and onions I air fried for 12 minutes at 400F. Since there wasn&rsquo;t a lot of these, they cooked quickly.</p>
<p>Both of these I left in the oven at 200F. I think this softened them further.</p>
<p>The pan-fried eggplants didn&rsquo;t turn out well. When I left them in the oven though, they softened up at least.</p>
<p>We put this all in wraps, along with leftover pork and cheese. We air-fried the wraps a few minutes since it&rsquo;s a nice way to crisp them up.</p>
<p><img src="images/20200825_184544.jpg" alt="Completed wraps"></p>
<h4 id="random-bits">Random bits</h4>
<p>I&rsquo;m not sure how these would be called in English. They&rsquo;re cubed root vegetables (potatoes, carrots, parsnips) with string beans and ham.</p>
<ul>
<li>Air fry mixed vegetables for 30 minutes at 400F, tossing often</li>
<li>Air fry beans and ham for 12 minutes at 400F, tossing twice</li>
</ul>
<p>This was alright. The beans were still crunchy in the middle, probably because the air fryer basket wasn&rsquo;t crowded. When you crowd the basket it tends to steam things rather than fry them, which helps some food soften.</p>
<p><img src="images/20200826_185050.jpg" alt="Completed wraps"></p>
<h3 id="future">Future</h3>
<p>I&rsquo;m going to try more eggplants! I hadn&rsquo;t known that they&rsquo;re very tasty when thoroughly cooked.</p>
<p>If I put less eggplant in the basket, will they cook and dry faster? It&rsquo;s worth a try.</p>
]]></content></item><item><title>More experiments in garlic fingers</title><link>https://sjchiass.github.io/website/posts/food/2020_w35_food/</link><pubDate>Sun, 23 Aug 2020 15:30:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sjchiass.github.io/website/posts/food/2020_w35_food/</guid><description>Needs more garlic butter!</description><content type="html"><![CDATA[<h3 id="past-week">Past week</h3>
<h4 id="garlic-fingers">Garlic fingers</h4>
<p>I continue my quest to make authentic maritime garlic fingers. This time I added bacon bits to the mix.</p>
<ul>
<li>Dough tossed in olive oil</li>
<li>1.5 tsp of garlic butter</li>
<li>A good 1/2&quot; of shredded cheese on top</li>
<li>Premade bacon bits to taste</li>
<li>Bake at 550F for 10 minutes, broil for 2 minutes</li>
<li>Top with dried basil</li>
</ul>
<p><img src="images/20200822_182702.jpg" alt="Uncooked fingers"></p>
<p>They turned out tasty but not perfect. I think I need to add a lot more garlic butter. I maybe used 1.5 teaspoons but should have gone with a tablespoon or so.</p>
<p><img src="images/20200822_184557.jpg" alt="Uncooked fingers"></p>
<p>Nevertheless, it was tasty. The crust was good, and there was a lot of cheese. Thanks to the grease it wasn&rsquo;t dry at all, so you could eat nearly the whole thing.</p>
<h4 id="pizza">Pizza</h4>
<p>I also decided to try a small pizza with the leftover dough.</p>
<ul>
<li>Dough tossed in olive oil</li>
<li>Cover with pasta sauce</li>
<li>1/2&quot; of cheese</li>
<li>A few leaves of basil</li>
<li>Generously cover with cut salami</li>
<li>Bake at 550F for 12 minutes, broil for 2 minutes</li>
</ul>
<p><img src="images/20200822_183610.jpg" alt="Uncooked pizza"></p>
<p>The best part was the pepperoni style salami I used. Compared to the usual pizza pepperoni, this &ldquo;pepperoni-style&rdquo; salami has a clear paprika taste. I had been eating it cold, but now I&rsquo;ve seen that it&rsquo;s also great slightly roasted.</p>
<p><img src="images/20200822_185840.jpg" alt="Cooked pizza"></p>
<h3 id="future">Future</h3>
<p>I think the garlic fingers need one of two things: more garlic butter or more garlic. The extra garlic could come from a garlic paste.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;m pretty sure the maritime garlic fingers are made with margarine mixed with garlic (paste?) and basil/oregano. While I think butter is great, the margarine might get closer to the correct texture and taste. It&rsquo;s possible that the extra moisture in margarine has an interesting effect.</p>
]]></content></item><item><title>A disapointing Amazon voltmeter/ammeter</title><link>https://sjchiass.github.io/website/posts/electronics/2020_w35_electronics/</link><pubDate>Sun, 23 Aug 2020 14:57:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sjchiass.github.io/website/posts/electronics/2020_w35_electronics/</guid><description>A disapointing Amazon voltmeter/ammeter. I feel like I got less than I paid for, but maybe I&amp;rsquo;ve been spoiled by cheap and convenient electronics.</description><content type="html"><![CDATA[<h3 id="past-week">Past week</h3>
<p>I started playing with the $10 voltmeter/ammeter I got from Amazon. It seems neat at first, but its lack of precision makes it less useful (or rather, useless). I don&rsquo;t see the use of this for electronics.</p>
<p><img src="images/20200821_073646.jpg" alt="A simple meter"></p>
<p>I rigged up a tupperware container to house it. Out the back I have lug connectors for the power supply and at the front I have headers for jumper wires. There are back connectors for 5V (meter&rsquo;s supply), positive voltage, and ground.</p>
<p>Unfortunately, the meter is not very accurate for electronics. The voltage resolution is only 0.1V, and it seems to underestimate lower voltages.</p>
<p>The ammeter only activates at about 0.10A and underestimates these lower current values. I had to add a bunch of 1k ohm resistors in parallel to get a reading.</p>
<p><img src="images/20200823_141546.jpg" alt="18V at 0.06A"></p>
<p>While I was trying to coax a current reading from the meter, I got to burn a resistor. Poor guy gave up his magic smoke.</p>
<p><img src="images/vlcsnap-2020-08-23-08h19m15s697.png" alt="Charred resistor"></p>
<p>On close-up, the paint is what seems to have burned. I&rsquo;m actually curious what its resistance is. It was originally 47 ohms.</p>
<p><img src="images/vlcsnap-2020-08-23-08h22m44s065.png" alt="Charred resistor"></p>
<p>I got out my multimeter to have a look! From 47 ohms it dropped down to about 30 ohms. Poor fellow lost more than a third of his vitality.</p>
<p><img src="images/20200823_151023.jpg" alt="Charred resistance"></p>
<h3 id="next-week">Next week</h3>
<p>I may investigate making my own voltmeter from an atmega-328. Its analog pins convert a 0V-5V analog signal into 1024 levels. This can be output to a small LCD screen and do about the same thing as my Amazon voltmeter.</p>
<p>With a voltage divider, the range can be extended to 0-30V. It would be able to measure whatever my power supply gives.</p>
<p>More interesting for electronics would be to have it measure around 5V. Depending on how extreme I expect voltage drops to be, it could hang around 4-6V and give decent resolution (2mV).</p>
<p>Since I&rsquo;m new to electronics, it&rsquo;s nice to have examples to work off from. This guide gives lots of useful information: <a href="https://www.instructables.com/id/Oscilloscope-in-a-Matchbox-Arduino/">https://www.instructables.com/id/Oscilloscope-in-a-Matchbox-Arduino/</a></p>
<p>Step 11 of the above guide has a simple voltmeter.</p>
]]></content></item><item><title>Starting a new container of plants on top of a bookcase</title><link>https://sjchiass.github.io/website/posts/plants/2020_w35_plants/</link><pubDate>Sun, 23 Aug 2020 14:31:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sjchiass.github.io/website/posts/plants/2020_w35_plants/</guid><description>The Next Generation</description><content type="html"><![CDATA[<h3 id="past-week">Past week</h3>
<p>I got some bigger containers from the dollar store to grow the plants in. I tried following the intructions on the seed packet by putting the seeds deeper into the soil. This caused some issues as we&rsquo;ll see below.</p>
<p>After only a few days the grass was able to break out from underground; though they had to do some heavy lifting in the process. As the plants have pushed upwards, the soil has overflowed the container.</p>
<p><img src="images/20200823_135413.jpg" alt="Five days of growth"></p>
<p>My setup is pretty cheap. Just a lamp and a small fan suspended/attached by surplus 2x4 lumber. The contraption is on top of a bookshelf, so I get to climb a stepladder each time I want to see. (A minor source of recreation during the work day.)</p>
<p>(The light is on a timer: on from 6AM to 10PM.)</p>
<p><img src="images/20200823_135428.jpg" alt="The growing setup"></p>
<p>I think I should have only put 1cm of soil over the seeds. They seem to start too far below ground otherwise. I&rsquo;ve found that the shoots are a bit sharp when I touch them, so I imagine they&rsquo;ve learned to drill through earth to see the sun.</p>
<p>There is a bit of reflection in the photo, but you can see that a few plants have created an air pocket by pushing up against the soil</p>
<p><img src="images/20200823_135458.jpg" alt="The growing setup"></p>
<h3 id="next-week">Next week</h3>
<p>My current setup is pretty lacklustre. How could I improve it?</p>
<h4 id="data-collection">Data collection</h4>
<p>The setup would be more interesting if data were collected.</p>
<ul>
<li>Timelapse photos of the growing process.</li>
<li>Time-series data of soil humidity.</li>
<li>Measuring growth somehow?</li>
</ul>
<h4 id="hydroponics">Hydroponics</h4>
<p>It would be interesting to use hydroponics in an advantageous way. Rather than wasting soil, I could re-use a growing medium. Or if the growing medium is cheap and disposable, I can just throw it away.</p>
<p>I wonder if the seeds could be suspended in perforated paper towel or some other absorbent material. Would the roots dangle down or propagate horizontally? What about the grass blades having enough support to stay upright? Cheesecloth or burlap may work.</p>
<h4 id="grow-lamps">Grow lamps</h4>
<p>There are some cheap grow lamps on Amazon. Comparing them against normal light and sunlight could be interesting.</p>
]]></content></item><item><title>OBS; miscellaneous electronics</title><link>https://sjchiass.github.io/website/posts/electronics/2020_w34_electronics/</link><pubDate>Sun, 16 Aug 2020 20:34:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sjchiass.github.io/website/posts/electronics/2020_w34_electronics/</guid><description>OBS; miscellaneous electronics</description><content type="html"><![CDATA[<h3 id="obs-and-streaming">OBS and streaming</h3>
<p>I&rsquo;ve been able to set up OBS Studio to output its video to a webcam. This should let me share desktops during video calls and even switch between multiple webcams. OBS Studio is used for streaming.</p>
<p>Getting OBS to output to a webcam requires <a href="https://github.com/umlaeute/v4l2loopback">v4l2loopback</a>. It&rsquo;s a Linux kernel module that will create a virtual <code>/dev/video</code> device that can receive video data and make it available as a webcam feed. As far as Discord/Skype/etc knows, your stream will just be another webcam.</p>
<p>I was able to get <code>v4l2loopback</code> to work on Ubuntu 18.04 and Fedora 32. In both cases it turned out easier that expected: just <code>git clone</code>, <code>make</code>, and <code>sudo make install</code>. The documentation warns you about mixing kernel and kernel header versions (or Linux will &ldquo;spit in your eye&rdquo;), but I haven&rsquo;t had problems yet.</p>
<p>In order to use the loopback in OBS, you also need the <a href="https://github.com/CatxFish/obs-v4l2sink">obs-v4l2sink</a> OBS plugin. This was easy in Ubuntu 18.04, but Fedora 32 was troublesome. On Fedora you can build it easily enough, but it won&rsquo;t be recognized by OBS unless its install path is adjusted. See the discussion here: <a href="https://github.com/CatxFish/obs-v4l2sink/issues/42">https://github.com/CatxFish/obs-v4l2sink/issues/42</a> (I think the <code>sed</code> command fixed it for me.)</p>
<h3 id="voltmeter-and-ammeter">Voltmeter and ammeter</h3>
<p>Last week I was looking at a DROK brand voltage and current meter, but I afterwards discovered it had a minimum measurement threshold of 6.5V. This is too high for most of my electronics. Instead I went with a cheaper little unit.</p>
<p><img src="images/20200816_192308.jpg" alt="The meter connected to my power supply"></p>
<p>The ammeter must be connected after the load; otherwise it doesn&rsquo;t measure current properly. Rather than integrate it into the power supply, I think I&rsquo;m going to put the meter in a box and use it in-between the supply and the device/circuit. I can then just move it around as I want, like a multimeter.</p>
<p>I should also buy some of those USB multimeters. With some bodging they could work to measure the current draws of Arduinos.</p>
<h3 id="banana-plugs-and-alligator-clips">Banana plugs and alligator clips</h3>
<p>These are surprisingly hard to find (cheap) online. They&rsquo;d be nice to have for binding posts.</p>
<p>Small alligator clips are also handy. They&rsquo;re small enough to clip either around the back of the post, or through the hole in the front.</p>
<h3 id="powering-your-old-cellphone-directly">Powering your old cellphone directly</h3>
<p>My old phone&rsquo;s battery was dead, so I powered the phone directly and succeeded. This was a bit interesting. It&rsquo;s something that would be hard to do without a variable power supply, a multimeter, and some fine clip-on test leads.</p>
<p><img src="images/20200811_194900.jpg" alt="Clip-on test leads on the battery pins"></p>
<p>The neat thing about this is that the phone battery isn&rsquo;t meant to operate at 3.8V as I first thought. With a 3.8V supply the phone will power up but immediately power off: it thinks the battery is critically low. The phone will only be happy at 4.0V to 4.3V, with the higher voltage registering as a &ldquo;full&rdquo; battery.</p>
<p><img src="images/20200811_201008.jpg" alt="Powered phone at 4.2V"></p>
<p>The phone was easy to handle thanks to the good clip-on leads. Sadly, there was nothing important on the phone itself.</p>
]]></content></item><item><title>Plants attacked by cats</title><link>https://sjchiass.github.io/website/posts/plants/2020_w34_plants/</link><pubDate>Sun, 16 Aug 2020 20:34:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sjchiass.github.io/website/posts/plants/2020_w34_plants/</guid><description>Plants</description><content type="html"><![CDATA[<h3 id="past-work">Past work</h3>
<p>My first adventures in cat grass growing came to its natural end.</p>
<p>My cats ate it.</p>
<p>I had moved the grass to the window since the plants had gotten too tall for the small lamp. I had also added a small fan to make them sway in the breeze, which is supposed to exercise them and make them tougher.</p>
<p>I was able to keep the container there for most of the week, but the cats eventually discovered it! They were obsessed with gobbling it all up. (Probably because they were afraid the other would eat it first.)</p>
<p><img src="images/20200815_084221.jpg" alt="Cat attack!"></p>
<p>They only seem to enjoy the blades and not the stems. This leaves a few centimeters of the plants above the ground. I&rsquo;ll see if any are able to recover.</p>
<p>Here is a close-up of a cut grass blade. It looks to me like crushed areas are a darker green, while the clean cuts become dry and yellowed.</p>
<p><img src="images/vlcsnap-2020-08-16-18h58m20s641.png" alt="Grass damage"></p>
<p>Sometimes the cats will get most of it in their mouths and will start chewing. If they don&rsquo;t manage to break it off, it&rsquo;ll just stay slimy like the photo below. There will also be some leftover trace evidence. (I think I got sick after some of that stuff fell into my tea.)</p>
<p><img src="images/vlcsnap-2020-08-16-19h02m47s371.png" alt="A clue!"></p>
<p>I had wanted to take a close-up of the roots last time. This time they were a little beat-up and one had a small bug. The bug must have come from the potting soil. (I might have dropped some of that dirt into my tea&hellip; I was sick last week.)</p>
<p><img src="images/vlcsnap-2020-08-16-19h04m21s631.png" alt="A small white bug crawls on a root"></p>
<h3 id="this-week">This week</h3>
<p>I need to fix my plant growing setup. With some wood I&rsquo;ll build a structure for the light to come from higher above. I&rsquo;ll raise the plants or the structure with books, as needed. The important thing if for the light to come down directly.</p>
<p>At the store I was able to get a lightbulb receptacle that can plug into a wall outlet. As long as I&rsquo;m able to secure it (duct tape?), I can position my light source it more freely.</p>
<p><img src="images/20200816_193145.jpg" alt="A new stronger bulb with a receptacle"></p>
]]></content></item><item><title>Progress on both rpi temperatures and cat grass manufacturing</title><link>https://sjchiass.github.io/website/posts/plants/2020_w33_plants/</link><pubDate>Sun, 09 Aug 2020 19:44:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sjchiass.github.io/website/posts/plants/2020_w33_plants/</guid><description>Progress on both rpi temperatures and cat grass manufacturing.</description><content type="html"><![CDATA[<h3 id="past-work">Past work</h3>
<p>I germinated the seeds and planted them. They were slow to get going but now they&rsquo;re growing like, well, weeds.</p>
<p>Yesterday they were tiny.</p>
<p><img src="images/20200808_080757.jpg" alt="Small grass"></p>
<p>Today they&rsquo;ve grown an inch or two.</p>
<p><img src="images/20200809_175639.jpg" alt="Big grass"></p>
<p>For fun I plugged in my cheap USB microscope and had a look.</p>
<p>Here is a closeup of the grass blade.</p>
<p><img src="images/vlcsnap-2020-08-09-17h43m40s438.png" alt="Grass blade close-up"></p>
<p>The grass grows sheathed. It starts out as a white rounded stalk but opens to extend a wide green blade of grass.</p>
<p><img src="images/vlcsnap-2020-08-09-17h48m31s086.png" alt="Sheath"></p>
<p>My potting soil has what I think is perlite to help aerate it. Perlite is glass turned to a light foam-like state by heat. I think it may be a bit like popcorn? I used to use a lot of it when I was playing with hydroponics.</p>
<p><img src="images/vlcsnap-2020-08-09-17h50m21s554.png" alt="Perlite?"></p>
<h3 id="this-week">This week</h3>
<p>I&rsquo;m going to let it grow. I&rsquo;ve wondered a little whether I should get cheap grow lights from Amazon and see if they beat my current bulb or natural sunlight. Could be interesting.</p>
]]></content></item><item><title>rpi temperatures and cat grass</title><link>https://sjchiass.github.io/website/posts/electronics/2020_w33_electronics/</link><pubDate>Sun, 09 Aug 2020 19:44:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sjchiass.github.io/website/posts/electronics/2020_w33_electronics/</guid><description>Progress on both rpi temperatures and cat grass manufacturing.</description><content type="html"><![CDATA[<h3 id="past-work">Past work</h3>
<p>GitHub: <a href="https://github.com/sjchiass/pitemp">https://github.com/sjchiass/pitemp</a></p>
<p>I had been thinking a lot about the best way to get good temperature data for my raspberry pi temperature project, and it all worked out alright.</p>
<p>My old way of collecting data had an issue with heat building up in the case and having biased datasets for closed cases. The data was good for simulating day-to-day use, but in day-to-day use of a raspberry pi, those little plastic cases are little ovens. Here is the problematic data.</p>
<p>(Useful: <code>plt.tight_layout()</code> got the titles to stop writing over the other plots' axes.)</p>
<p><img src="images/timeseries.png" alt="Cases' time series"></p>
<p>As you can see above, the case heats up and stays hot for the duration of the test. The data isn&rsquo;t that great to figuring out how much heat the case dissipates. (I should come up with a measure of this bias, actually.)</p>
<p>The new script lets the case heat up to a maximum and then lets it cool down to a minimum. It waits 30 seconds before &ldquo;declaring&rdquo; the minimums and maximums. It does this for two hours. Here is the data. As you can see, much fairer to the closed cases.</p>
<p><img src="images/time_series_better.png" alt="Cases' time series improved"></p>
<p>I was also proud of this little graph showing the minimums and maximums. Nice colors and some reference lines.</p>
<p><img src="images/minmax_temps.png" alt="A nice bar chart of different case temperatures"></p>
<h3 id="this-week">This week</h3>
<p>I&rsquo;m going to keep cleaning up the analysis I&rsquo;ve bundled with the code and data.</p>
<p>I may try the new data collection method with more case configurations, like removing the side panels. I&rsquo;m also able to collect data on the heatsinks, but I haven&rsquo;t done that yet. Should be interesting: heatsinks probably benefit the most from fans and it&rsquo;d be interesting to measure the interaction there.</p>
<h2 id="other-things">Other things</h2>
<p>I found this interesting cheese at the store. I think it may be like the strange bottled cheese I found in Quebec truck stops. If my guess is correct, this will be very tough and salty cheese. It&rsquo;s not that pleasant to eat, but its saltiness satisfies junk food cravings.</p>
<p>Interestingly, the brand is Phoenicia, which implies this may be a kind of cheese popular in the Middle East. I found it next to the halloumi cheese.</p>
<p><img src="images/20200809_131912.jpg" alt="Cheese"></p>
<p>I think I&rsquo;m going to buy this $20 &ldquo;DROK&rdquo; volt, amp, watt and watt-hour display from Amazon and connect it to my Elenco bench power supply. It&rsquo;ll help me see the current draw of what I&rsquo;m powering from there. I&rsquo;ll have to test and see if it measures properly.</p>
<p><img src="images/voltmeter.jpg" alt="LCD meter"></p>
<p>Now I&rsquo;ll be able to measure voltage and current when playing with case fans! With only one multimeter, I can only measure or voltage at once. (And I have to move things around a bit.)</p>
<p><img src="images/20200704_192253.jpg" alt="Old setup"></p>
]]></content></item><item><title>I consider growing plants</title><link>https://sjchiass.github.io/website/posts/plants/2020_w32_plants/</link><pubDate>Tue, 04 Aug 2020 13:15:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sjchiass.github.io/website/posts/plants/2020_w32_plants/</guid><description>I consider growing plants.</description><content type="html"><![CDATA[<h3 id="past-work">Past work</h3>
<p>I&rsquo;ve had a 5V USB water pump and a soild humidity sensor for years, but I have never used them. I had thought of buying an aquarium to make a large safe test area.</p>
<p><img src="images/20200804_141653.jpg" alt="The pump and sensors"></p>
<h3 id="this-week">This week</h3>
<p>I bought a small bag of potting soil and a small bag of catgrass seeds for $4 each. I&rsquo;m going to start the seeds in the soil and see what happens. I&rsquo;ll use my daylight LED bulb as a light source. No need for special grow lights just yet!</p>
<p><img src="images/20200804_141743.jpg" alt="Cat grass seeds"></p>
<p>After I&rsquo;ve had a bit of practice, I want to try my soil humidity sensor. If that works, I can place the plants' tupperware in a bigger plastic container and start testing the USB pump.</p>
<p>I only want to start automating things once I&rsquo;m sure the sensor and the pump work well.</p>
<p>Thankfully I still have a timed outlet that I can use to control the light bulb. It should work fine.</p>
<h2 id="writing">Writing</h2>
<h3 id="past-work-1">Past work</h3>
<p>I&rsquo;ve written a few things for this website but have stopped.</p>
<h3 id="this-week-1">This week</h3>
<p>It&rsquo;s unlikely I&rsquo;ll stick to it, but I&rsquo;ve started writing about logical fallacies. I think the work of writing it is good, even if it&rsquo;s not something I finish.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;d also enjoy writing about Epictetus and Zen, but I&rsquo;m not sure anyone would find that interesting. At least logical fallacies excite the mind.</p>
<p>Of course, I&rsquo;ve also started writing these updates. (EDIT: this one has taken almost exactly one hour to write. Not bad.)</p>
<h2 id="other-things">Other things</h2>
<p>I&rsquo;ve modified the lighting for my electronics bench. I&rsquo;ve moved one of the spotlights up to the top of the structure. I found that light was in the way. Light now comes from all directions.</p>
<p><img src="images/20200804_141716.jpg" alt="Well-lit lab"></p>
<p>How do I find the desk lab? The easy access to the power supply and soldering station is great. The parts drawers are also convenient.</p>
<p>The bad part? The multimeter and its probes take up space and are always a mess.</p>
]]></content></item><item><title>Modelling pi temperatures</title><link>https://sjchiass.github.io/website/posts/electronics/2020_w32_electronics/</link><pubDate>Tue, 04 Aug 2020 13:15:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sjchiass.github.io/website/posts/electronics/2020_w32_electronics/</guid><description>I continue work on modelling pi temperatures</description><content type="html"><![CDATA[<h3 id="past-work">Past work</h3>
<p>I&rsquo;ve been logging CPU temperatures of my Raspberry Pi 3B+ for past several weeks. I add and remove parts of its case and run tests for hours. I&rsquo;ve put the data in OLS models to see how different components affect temperatures. I&rsquo;ve come to realize that this kind of modelling is &ldquo;descriptive&rdquo; but not too explanatory. This is because the data is generated from randomly stressing the CPU with 0/25/50/75/100% load. This data can answer the question &ldquo;what gets hot&rdquo; but now &ldquo;how much heat is evacuated by an open top&rdquo;?</p>
<p>My problem has been that different case configurations have wildly different temperature ranges. A narrow range of temperature means less variety, and less variety means less for a model to work with. Left alone, a fully closed case will slowly work its way to 80C and stay there. This kind of data isn&rsquo;t great because it only shows a cluster of temperatures: the CPU throttles itself and cannot go higher, and the closed case keeps the heat inside. The added problem is that the series is not stationary either. The temperature will fluctuate at first, but when it reaches its plateau it ceases to fluctuate: the range of temperature depends on how long the test has been running.</p>
<p><img src="images/timeseries.png" alt="Cases' time series"></p>
<p>My solution to this has been to add cooldown periods. Above a certain temperature, the script will make the CPU sleep until it lowers beneath a lower temperature bound. This should add some variety to closed cases since they&rsquo;ll now have more than one opportunity to build up heat. Note that this changes the nature of data: closed up cases will now stress the CPU less since they&rsquo;ll spend more of their time in cooldown. This may not not be realistic in terms of daily RaspBerry Pi use.</p>
<h3 id="this-week">This week</h3>
<p>I&rsquo;m going to keep playing with the modified script. I am only running it for open top, holed top, closed top, intake fan, and exhaust fan. Both side covers are on.</p>
<p><img src="images/20200804_141854.jpg" alt="A test underway"></p>
<p>The question is: how do I best adjust the script to capture good quality time series data? It&rsquo;s important that the CPU is allowed to build up heat, so cooldown cycles should not be started too soon (but too high and there is never cooldown). Latent case heat should be eliminated if possible, so the CPU should cool down to a fairly low temperature (50-55C) before working again.</p>
<p>A bit of an annoying problem is that cases with fans neither reach high temperatures nor cool down very fast. How do I add more variety to their temperatures? I could enforce cooldowns at regular intervals, regardless of temperature. However, I should have a look at the data before going this route.</p>
]]></content></item><item><title>My First Smoked Pulled Pork</title><link>https://sjchiass.github.io/website/posts/food/2020_w29_food/</link><pubDate>Fri, 26 Jun 2020 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sjchiass.github.io/website/posts/food/2020_w29_food/</guid><description>My first attempt at making smoked pulled pork on the charcoal BBQ.</description><content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Last summer I had the pleasure of trying lots of smoked BBQ pulled pork, so this year I decided to try cooking it myself. The results were quite good even if I only smoked the meat for 2 hours. The rub, the sauce, and a bit of smoke flavour made for great little sandwiches. If I were to try the recipe again, I would smoke the meat longer to get more of that rich applewood flavor.</p>
<p>The pulled pork was great in a slice of bread. It was tender, tangy, and flavourful.</p>
<p><img src="images/20200626_192839.jpg" alt="The pulled pork sandwich"></p>
<h2 id="lessons">Lessons</h2>
<ul>
<li>Too much rub ends up burning</li>
<li>If you inject liquid into the meat, too much pressure will shoot the liquid back at you</li>
<li>A longer smoke would give more flavour</li>
<li>Make sure to identify your smoking wood beforehand (label it mesquite, applewood, hickory, etc.)</li>
<li>Better coal management could mean less ash</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="ingredients">Ingredients</h2>
<p>We got a 1kg pork shoulder boneless blade roast from the grocery store. It was a medium-sized block of fatty meat. When I started manipulated it, I noticed that some cords were used to bind it together.</p>
<p><img src="images/20200626_134045.jpg" alt="The raw meat"></p>
<p>For the rub I decided to follow a recipe. This rub was great, and I&rsquo;ve since used it on other meats! It has a nice red pepper and garlic taste, with a bit of heat from the cayenne. The original recipe asked for regular paprika, but I used smoked paprika instead, which must have contributed to some of the flavour. (Smoked paprika has a similar taste to some brands of BBQ potato chips.)</p>
<p>For the sauce I used a mustard BBQ sauce. I love mustard! This sauce was a bit strong due to the apple cider vinegar, but when added to the meat the flavour is subdued.</p>
<h3 id="memphis-style-rub">Memphis-style rub</h3>
<p>Adapted from: <a href="https://www.thespruceeats.com/memphis-bbq-rub-335875">https://www.thespruceeats.com/memphis-bbq-rub-335875</a></p>
<ul>
<li>1/8 cup smoked paprika powder</li>
<li>1/8 cup cayenne pepper powder</li>
<li>1/8 cup garlic powder</li>
<li>1/8 cup chili powder</li>
<li>1 teaspoon salt</li>
<li>1 teaspoon ground black pepper</li>
<li>1 teaspoon onion powder</li>
<li>1 teaspoon celery salt</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="carolina-style-bbq-sauce">Carolina-style BBQ sauce</h3>
<p>Adapted from: <a href="https://www.thespruceeats.com/big-daddy-carolina-style-barbecue-sauce-333684">https://www.thespruceeats.com/big-daddy-carolina-style-barbecue-sauce-333684</a></p>
<ul>
<li>1/2 cup apple cider vinegar</li>
<li>3/8 cup brown sugar</li>
<li>1/4 cup grainy dijon mustard</li>
<li>1/4 cup yellow prepared mustard</li>
<li>1/8 cup water</li>
<li>1 tablespoon of rub</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="preparation">Preparation</h2>
<p>I mixed the ingredients of the rub together and sprinkled 1/4 cup of it onto the meat in a bowl. By working the meat with my hands, I was able to spread it over the surface.</p>
<p><img src="images/20200626_134520.jpg" alt="The rub applied"></p>
<p>I had bought a new meat injector at the store, so I was excited to try it out! I mixed 2 teaspoons of my rub mixture into 1/4 cup of water in a bowl. I then started injecting the liquid mixture but quickly had it shot back at me! A pretty embarassing mess-up on my end. (The shirt stains weren&rsquo;t permanent thankfully.)</p>
<p>What went wrong with the injections? When I was doing it, it took a bit of pressure on the plunger to move the mixture into the meat, but the syringe itself didn&rsquo;t feel much of it. When I withdrew the needle, the pressure I added through the plunger was released.</p>
<p>It seems to be that you shouldn&rsquo;t try to put too much into the meat, and you may be fine letting the liquid drip in without plunger pressure. The lack of quantity can be made up with more numerous injections over the meat.</p>
<p>When I was done with the injections the meat and the rub were a bit soggy. I put the meat in a ziploc bag and in the fridge. When I brought it outside, I made sure to have an ice pack next to it.</p>
<p><img src="images/20200626_140401.jpg" alt="Meat post-injection"></p>
<h2 id="cooking">Cooking</h2>
<p>This was cooked on a 18&quot; Weber &ldquo;Jumbo Joe&rdquo; charcoal grill. Since I was finishing my bag of briquette charcoal, I mixed in half hardwood charcoal. This I used to fill a large Weber charcoal chimney. It&rsquo;s possible that the quantity of charcoal was a bit too much, and I will report back how well a smaller amount works.</p>
<p><img src="images/20200626_144902.jpg" alt="Charcoal chimney in use"></p>
<p>Now when it came to picking my smoking wood, I discovered that I hadn&rsquo;t labelled any of it last year! By looking at the chunks closely, I thought I was able to identify the hickory and the applewood. Applewood has a light grey bark while the hickory wood is lighter and brighter. I think I guessed correctly, but I couldn&rsquo;t say for sure. I suspect I may have picked pecan and mesquite instead. <strong>Label your smoking woods!</strong></p>
<p>I used both woods in turn. First the hickory, then the applewood. (I burned some on the side while cooking to try to identify them by the smoke.)</p>
<p>The BBQ I set up by pushing the coals to one side and putting water cups under the grill on the other side. On top of the coals I put the wood chunks and over the water I put the meat. The water is there discourage drying the meat.</p>
<p><img src="images/20200626_152740.jpg" alt="Meat on the grill"></p>
<p>During the smoke I kept track of the temperatures with two thermometers. I used a shorter BBQ thermometer to measure the inside air temperature (300F to 350F is ideal). I also used a longer candy thermometer to pierce the meat and monitor its temperature (it should increase slowly over time up to 175F).</p>
<p><img src="images/20200626_153347.jpg" alt="Photo of thermometer setup"></p>
<p>An hour later I opened the cover to add more smoking wood chunks and water to the cups. The meat had already started looking tastier. I want to point out here how much grease has already melted into the water, which still manages to boil visibly with bubbles escaping through the fat. I discovered later that this grease can catch fire if it drips into the coals, so be careful!</p>
<p><img src="images/20200626_163039.jpg" alt="Meat after an hour"></p>
<p>Since I think I put too much coal, I was worried that there was too much ash. I lifted the grill and put it aside, and then I quickly moved the coals to the other side of the grill. This eliminated the ash building up in the coals and hopefully made it easier for them to burn. Too much ash means not enough air and so not enough heat, a situation that can mean a stalled BBQ.</p>
<p>By the end of the smoke, the rub was looking a bit charred. This doesn&rsquo;t seem to have affected the flavour, but it&rsquo;s a bit worrisome.</p>
<p><img src="images/20200626_171659.jpg" alt="Meat after 1.5 hours"></p>
<h2 id="serving">Serving</h2>
<p>I wrapped the meat in a foil container and left it in the oven at 300F. As you can see below, there were still some juices in there.</p>
<p><img src="images/bbq/20200626_184504.jpg" alt="Meat wrapped up and kept warm in the oven"></p>
<p>The BBQ sauce was straightforward. Simply mix the ingredients and simmer for 20 minutes, stirring frequently. The brown sugar will cook with the mustard a bit. It is a pungeant sauce, and you&rsquo;ll smell the vinegar and mustard.</p>
<p><img src="images/20200626_190313.jpg" alt="The sauce before being cooked"></p>
<p>I found that the pork shoulder had lots of fat. This made it easy to separate into chunks, but I found that I had to spend some time to &ldquo;fork&rdquo; the chunks individually. The sauce was absorbed by the meat and the two became a chunky mixture that was easy to scoop onto bread.</p>
<p><img src="images/20200626_192833.jpg" alt="Pulling the pork with sauce"></p>
<h2 id="results">Results</h2>
<p>The rub and the sauce made a tasty combination. The strong tang from the mustard and vinegar were partially offset by the garlic and spice from the rub. The high fat content of the meat made it very smooth. Unfortunately, there was not a lot of smoke flavour.</p>
<p><img src="images/20200626_193156.jpg" alt="The resulting sandwich"></p>
]]></content></item><item><title>A Very Short Introduction: Teeth</title><link>https://sjchiass.github.io/website/posts/misc/2018_w40_books/</link><pubDate>Sat, 06 Oct 2018 23:21:28 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://sjchiass.github.io/website/posts/misc/2018_w40_books/</guid><description>My review of a Very Short Introduction: Teeth</description><content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>A Very Short Introduction: Teeth</em> is my 28th VSI book read, and I enjoyed it. I had picked it up to read before my dentist&rsquo;s appointment, so that I would understand teeth terminology better. Since the book gives a nice wide introduction to teeth, I found that I ended up learning many things as well. I&rsquo;ll have to see if there&rsquo;s a VSI on dentistry.</p>
<p>This VSI has a well-defined topic (teeth), covers multiple aspects of teeth (function, evolution, humans), and is a clear and understandable read. What I found most interesting was the evolution of teeth, how teeth cusps slowly reconfigure themselves. Once in a while I feel the sharpness of my teeth and recall that certain animals have self-sharpening teeth. While the knowledge may not be practical, but it was still interesting for me to learn.</p>
<ul>
<li>Book: <a href="https://global.oup.com/academic/product/teeth-a-very-short-introduction-9780199670598">https://global.oup.com/academic/product/teeth-a-very-short-introduction-9780199670598</a></li>
</ul>
<h3 id="teeth-matter">Teeth matter</h3>
<p>In the introductory chapter, the author outlines why teeth are interesting. I find that he does a good job here.</p>
<p>His first argument is that teeth are cool. Teeth are part of a &ldquo;perpetual death match in the mouth&rdquo; because they continue to evolve to be sharper, tougher and stronger to chew plants and animals, who sometimes evolve to counteract teeth (ie: harder insect exoskeleton).</p>
<p>Teeth are noticeable. Whether it&rsquo;s the small teeth of a kitten or the large teeth of a predator, or the smile of another human being, our attention is drawn to teeth. Personally I find it fascinating to see cats' small incisor teeth since they&rsquo;re so tiny compared to ours.</p>
<p><img src="images/20190622_163610(0)_cropped.jpg" alt="My cat&rsquo;s teeth"></p>
<p>Teeth have an evolutionary significance too. Before teeth, organisms would filter nutrients and not much else. What teeth allowed was the crushing of food sources to get at the nutrients within. Teeth further evolved in terms of efficiency (better tearing flesh) or in response to the defenses of prey.</p>
<p>Teeth are also important to our lives. Mammals are endoterms so they rely a lot on teeth to get at nutrients. If human beings did not have good teeth, they would be a lot less effective at extracting energy from food. Human beings could not simulatenously tear meats, chew vegetables, and crunch candies without well-developed teeth.</p>
<p>Teeth are often the only fossils of extinct animals such as dinosaurs. The teeth are hard bones with extra protection, so they are preserved better.</p>
<h3 id="types-and-parts-of-teeth">Types and parts of teeth</h3>
<p>The author covers a lot of technical information and terminology. When the chapter got into more specific teminology I got lost. The authors talks about the history and controversy of paracones, metacones, and tribosphenic molars for a few pages.</p>
<p>Different organisms have different teeth. They may either grow their teeth once, twice, or multiple times. The first teeth are called baby, milk or deciduous, and for some animals these are permanent. For organisms with multiple sets, the baby teeth can either fall off in the womb or later in life. Teeth may all be identical, which are called homodont, or they can be different, which are called heterodont.</p>
<p>Mammalian teeth are heterodont, meaning that they&rsquo;re different. Incisors are the flat front teeth used for cutting. Canine are sharper needle-like teeth for tearing (their shape vary). Pre-molars are the first of the &ldquo;cheek teeth&rdquo; (or post-canines) and vary in usage. The molars seem to mostly be for crushing. These can be quite different in different mammals. In cats the pre-molars are for slicing and the canines are longer. In herbivores the canines can be flatter, like extra incisors.</p>
<p>The amount of these types of teeth in a mammal vary. Humans are identified by I2/2, C1/1, P2/2, M3/3 (2+2 incisors, 1+1 canines, 2+2 pre-molars and 3+3 molars). Note that wisdom teeth are the third set of molars, and you may have had yours removed.</p>
<p>There are terms used to identify locations on teeth.</p>
<ul>
<li>For the front teeth, the front side is <em>labial</em> and the back side is <em>lingual</em>.</li>
<li>Towards the middle of the front teeth is called <em>mesial</em> and away from it if <em>distal</em>.</li>
<li>For the back or post-canine teeth, towards the front is <em>anterior</em> and towards the back is <em>posterior</em>.</li>
<li>Tongue side of the back teeth is <em>lingual</em> and away from the tongue is <em>buccal</em>.</li>
<li>The biting side (towards the biting) is called the <em>occlusal</em> surface.</li>
</ul>
<p>The vocabulary for occlusal surfaces is quite complicated, and unfortunately, partly misleading. Terms such as <em>paracone</em>, <em>metacone</em>, <em>protocone</em> and <em>hypocone</em> were supposed to correspond to how the <em>cusps</em> of the teeth evolved, but the names turned out not to match exactly. There is more information in the book.</p>
<p>Teeth are made of <em>enamel</em>, <em>dentine</em>, <em>cementum</em> and <em>pulp</em>. Enamel is the toughest material, at 95% mineral content, and it forms the biting surface. Dentine constitutes most of a tooth and is still a tough material. Cementum is found at the root and sometimes at the crown. The pulp fills out a tooth with blood vessels, nerves and other soft tissue.</p>
<h3 id="what-teeth-do-food-and-feeding">What teeth do: food and feeding</h3>
<p>This is a fun chapter. The author starts by going over what kind of nutrients and micronutrients are found in different food sources and how these different food sources require different teeth. By associating food with teeth and teeth with animal, the author gives examples that readers can easily follow and even visualize.</p>
<p>Plant matter can be leaves, fruits, roots, and grasses, and these different items require different kinds of teeth to eat them. Fruits can be pulped, but grasses might need to be eaten twice. Some animals regurgitate food in order to chew it a second time. For carnivores, meat must be sliced and chewed, and it tends to be easier to digest; however, teeth might need to be specialized for attacking and immobilizing prey.</p>
<p>Teeth and mastication interact with the digestive system. More chewing exposes more nutrients to the digestive system, but it also tends to make food move faster through it. For certain foods that are not digestible directly, slow movement through the digestive system encourages more fermentation. With ruminants, for examples, grasses are chewed and then passed through multiple stomachs. It&rsquo;s important to &ldquo;choose&rdquo; the appropriate amount of chewing so that the digestive system gets the optimal input.</p>
<p>The teeth of animals are therefore useful for infering the diet of animals. Primates that husk large fruits have larger incisors. Grazers that eat higher volumes of grasses have broader incisors than more selective grazers. Cats have sharper canines than dogs. Some animals have tusks, and some animals use their teeth for digging or grooming. Teeth give helpful clues to the characteristics of these animals.</p>
<h3 id="teeth-before-the-mammals">Teeth before the mammals</h3>
<p>This chapter is a historical summary of teeth. The author lists examples and includes visual aids to help the reader follow along.</p>
<p>There are two possibilities of the origin of teeth for mammals, either the outside-in or the inside-out hypotheses. In the outside-in possibility, teeth would have originated as sharp bony plates near the mouth, similar to shark scales. <em>Ostracoderms</em> are such ancient fish with these bony scales. In the inside-out hypothesis, <em>conodonts</em> had teeth-like things in their throats to help process food, and these proto-teeth would have migrated into the mouth.</p>
<p>Moving forward through time, the trend as been for teeth to migrate to the jaw and attach themselves there. Fish (and reptiles to a lesser extent) can have teeth spread out through the mouth and sometimes in the throat. But mammals keep their teeth at the margin of the mouth.</p>
<p>How teeth are attached also differ. Fish have their teeth attached to the bone. Crocodiles have teeth growing out of bone sockets. If I understand right, mammals have some kind of ligament and bone sockets that fill themselves out in adulthood.</p>
<p>Over time the trend is towards fewer and more specialized teeth, but there is a lot of variety out there. Fish have lots of different types of teeth. While crocodiles just have lots of pegs, some dinosaurs had what the author calls &ldquo;dental division of labor&rdquo;, different types of teeth in the same mouth.</p>
<h3 id="the-evolution-of-teeth-in-mammals">The evolution of teeth in mammals</h3>
<p>The chapter starts with an interesting fact: the <em>amniotes</em> evolved an egg that could be laid and hatched on dry land. These amniotes split into groups distinguished by the amount of holes on the sides of their skulls; anapsids without holes, synapsids with one (mammals), and diapsids with two (reptiles). The pelycosaurs (a group that includes the reptile-like creatures with a fan on their backs) were synapsids that were successful until the arrival of the dinosaurs. Wikipedia has some more information about this; birds are diapsids</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Anapsid">https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Anapsid</a></li>
<li><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Synapsid">https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Synapsid</a></li>
<li><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Diapsid">https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Diapsid</a></li>
</ul>
<p>What made mammals develop specialized teeth was the higher energy requirements of having to generate heat and supply energy to brains needing to analyze better senses of taste and smell. Throughout the chapter the impression is that mammalian teeth evolution was a free-for-all.</p>
<p>Mammalian skulls and jaws evolved to better attach muscles for chewing. Muscles needed to work together so that chewing motions could go from side to side and shift around. The jaw joint evolved into the <em>temporomandibular joint</em> (TMJ), which had the side benefit of letting a few bones split off and become the bones of the inner ear.</p>
<p>Another evolution was the hard bony palate, which makes separating the nasal passage a surer thing. It also helps food move around the mouth with some help from the tongue.</p>
<p>When dinosaurs ruled the land and mammals became small nocturnal insectivores, their teeth specialized to eat insects. This changed things and I think wikipedia even called this the <em>nocturnal bottleneck</em> of mammalian evolution.</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nocturnal_bottleneck">https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nocturnal_bottleneck</a></li>
</ul>
<p>The rest of the chapter is spent talking about the evolution of particular tooth shapes. The takeaway message for me is that there was a lot of change. Certain shapes appeared and dissappeared forever, like the saber-toothed cat&rsquo;s cheek teeth the shape of single long horizontal blades. I think that since mammalian teeth are so specialized (and also crucial to breaking down food extra efficiently) it makes sense they&rsquo;d evolve quickly.</p>
<p>I enjoyed this chapter. I&rsquo;ve been drawn to dinosaur teeth because they&rsquo;re large, monstrous and cool, like the author alluded to in the introductionary chapter. Nevertheless the adult me now appreciates the subtleties of mammalian teeth.</p>
<h3 id="mammalian-teeth-today">Mammalian teeth today</h3>
<p>The author jumps back to the present, after having spent two chapters in history.</p>
<p>Mammalian teeth are diverse because properly chewed food is crucial to satisfy the energy needs of endothermy. When at rest, warm-blooded animals use about 5 to 10 times the amount of energy of a cold-blooded animal.</p>
<p>This chapter goes over the different teeth of the marsupials, and the placental xenarthrans, afrotherians, laurasiatherians, and euarchontoglirians. The laurasiatherians have the most variety in teeth and include whales, pigs, cats, dogs, horses, and shrews. The euarchontoglirians include rodents and primates and have the greater number of species despite having smaller teeth variation; rodents have chisel incisors and flat cheek teeth.</p>
<h3 id="human-teeth-and-their-history">Human teeth and their history</h3>
<p>The chapter&rsquo;s message seems to be that most of the difference is between hominid teeth and the rest of the primates. Chimpanzees and gorillas have large canines for fighting and cheek teeth for leaves and fruits, while humans are more omnivorous.</p>
<p>Apparently humans have thicker enamel, but what this means is unclear.</p>
<p>The author says that current human diet has changed faster than evolution can keep up. Humans have a lot more dental caries than other primates and other animals. Humans also have overbite because of smaller jaws, likely because we are chewing softer foods. Apparently the changes in caries and overbite can happen in a generation from when foragers adopt a western diet.</p>
<p>I found it interesting to hear that human foragers don&rsquo;t have the overbite we do, and their front teeth &ldquo;occlude&rdquo; better. Each time I read that paragraph, I push my jaw forward and try to figure out how &ldquo;normal&rdquo; teeth would fit together.</p>
<h3 id="endless-forms">Endless forms</h3>
<p>This is just a summary of things already dicussed in the book, such as the evolution of teeth, how they&rsquo;re made, and the relationship between diet, circumstance and teeth.</p>
]]></content></item></channel></rss>